<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>The seafood markets in the northern mediterranean countries</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Paquotte, Philippe</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Guillard, Valerie</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>Economics</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Consumption</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>International trade</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Sea products</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>SEM</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Economie</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Consommation</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Commerce extérieur</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Produits de la mer</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>A brief survey of the sea-food markets for the northern Mediterranean countries is presented, i.e. for Cyprus, France, Greece, Italy, Portugal, Spain and Turkey. Then a comparative study between the markets belonging to the European Union is completed. Three of these countries (France, Italy and Spain) are characterised by a huge deficit in their external sea-products trade. Greece is almost balanced, but Portugal has been importing increasingly more over the last few years. About 45% of the imports come from the European Union. After many years of increasing value, we can now see a stabilisation in the fish price. Since 1977, the consumption of fresh products has been receding in favour of frozen and processed products. Cultured salmon and shrimp which were less popular a few years ago are now two of the most important sea food items, especially in France, which indicates that these markets are eager to consume products from aquaculture. The distribution channels are still traditional for fresh fish in these countries except in France where supermarkets account for more than 50% of retail sales. The difficulty of gathering homogeneous and reliable information reveals the importance of implementing a network devoted to these data. [NOT CONTROLLED OCR]</dc:description>
  <dc:description>Après une rapide description des marchés des produits de la mer des pays du nord de la Méditerranée, c'est à dire Chypre, Espagne, France, Grèce, Italie, Portugal et Turquie, ce travail présente une étude comparative des marchés appartenant à l'Union Européenne. Trois de ces pays (Espagne, Italie et France) sont caractérisés par un énorme déficit de la balance du commerce extérieur des produits de la mer. La Grèce est à peu près équilibrée mais le Portugal importe de plus en plus depuis quelques années. A peu près 45% des importations viennent de l'Union Européenne. Après des années de croissance en valeur, on peut désormais observer une stabilisation du prix du poisson. Depuis 1977, la part des produits frais dans la consommation se réduit au profit des produits congelés et transformés. Les saumons et les crevettes d'élevage qui avaient une position marginale il y a quelques années sont devenus des produits de grande consommation, surtout en France, ce qui montre les potentialités de ces marchés pour les produits d'élevage. Les circuits de distribution sont restés traditionnels pour le poisson frais dans ces pays sauf en France où les grandes surfaces assurent désormais plus de 50% des ventes. La difficulté pour obtenir des données homogènes et fiables révèle la nécessité de mettre en place un réseau consacré à ce genre d'informations. [OCR NON CONTRÔLE]</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>Actes du SELAM seminar on aquaculture marketing, Thessaloniki, October 1995</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>1995-10</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Conference article</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/1995/acte-4055.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:language>en</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/4055/</dc:relation>
</oai_dc:dc>