<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>REMONOR : résultats 2005. Evaluation de la mortalité, croissance et qualité des huîtres creuses</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Mary, Charlotte</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Pien, S</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Blin, J.l.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Ropert, Michel</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>REMORA</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>quality</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>growth</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>mortality</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Normandy</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>REMONOR</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Cupped (gigas) oyster</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Crassostrea gigas</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>REMORA</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Qualité</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Croissance</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Mortalité</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Basse Normandie</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>REMONOR</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Huître creuse</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Crassostrea gigas</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>The regional monitoring network REMONOR, relying on the experience of IFREMER's REMORA national network, each year assesses the mortality, growth and quality for two age classes ("adults" = 2 years and "juveniles" = 1 year) of cup oysters, distributed among various farm sites in the main oyster farming sectors of Lower Normandy.

This network, led in collaboration by LERN (Environment Resources Laboratory) and SMEL (Coastline Installations Public-Private Entity), this year welcomes a new farm site in Veules les Roses, in Seine Maritime (76), bringing to 18 the total number of monitored sites. For operational reasons, a reduced monitoring protocol was conducted in 2005 on this last farm site, which will not take on the network's standardised protocol until 2006. It is subject to processing and partial analysis for this first year.

The number of mortalities observed in 2005 is low and confirms the trend noted since 2002. The regional averages are in fact 6.6% for the adults and 7.7% for the juveniles. With the exception of the juveniles in North Gouville (CO07), whose mortality is probably random, no rate was higher than 12%.

A contrario, overall growth is not good, with an average individual weight in December of 58g for the adults. This trend mainly affects the whole of the West Coast of Cotentin (with the exception of Chausey). For the juveniles, the average individual weight in December is slightly lower than the average recorded since 1998. It is in Calvados (Bay of Les Veys and Meuvaines) that the growth deficits are the most significant for this age class.

On a qualitative level, the AFNOR index is, in the whole of the region, lower than the average over several years (10.7 in 2005 against 11.5 since 1993). This reduction of quality is especially noticeable on the Cotentin east coast and in the Bay of Les Veys. The results concerning the infestations by Polydora are, however, excellent and 2005 is proving itself to be the best year since REMONOR's beginning because of the low levels of infestation observed.</dc:description>
  <dc:description>Le réseau régional de suivi REMONOR s'appuyant sur les acquis du réseau national REMORA de l'Ifremer, évalue chaque année la mortalité, la croissance et la qualité sur deux classes d'âges (« adultes » = 2 ans et « juvéniles » = 1 an) d'huîtres creuses, réparties entre différentes stations dans les principaux secteurs ostréicoles Bas-Normands.

Ce réseau, mené en collaboration entre le LERN (Laboratoire Environnement Ressources de Normandie) et le SMEL (Syndicat Mixte de L'Equipement du Littoral), accueille cette année une nouvelle station à Veules les Roses, en Seine Maritime (76), portant à 18 le nombre total de sites suivis. Pour des raisons opérationnelles, un protocole de suivi allégé a été mené en 2005 sur cette dernière station qui n'intègrera le protocole standardisé du réseau qu'en 2006. Elle fait l'objet d'un traitement et d'une analyse partielle pour cette première année.

Les mortalités observées en 2005 sont faibles et confirment la tendance relevée depuis 2002. Les moyennes régionales sont en effet de 6,6% pour les adultes et de 7,7% pour les juvéniles. A l'exception des juvéniles à Gouville Nord (CO07), dont la mortalité est probablement accidentelle, aucun taux n'est supérieur à 12%

A contrario, la croissance générale n'est pas bonne, avec un poids moyen individuel en décembre de 58g pour les adultes. Cette tendance touche essentiellement l'ensemble de la Côte Ouest du Cotentin (à l'exception de Chausey). Pour les juvéniles, le poids moyen individuel en décembre est légèrement inférieur à la moyenne enregistrée depuis 1998. C'est dans le Calvados (Baie des Veys et Meuvaines) que les déficits de croissance sont les plus importants pour cette classe d'âge.

Sur un plan qualitatif, l'indice AFNOR est, dans l'ensemble de la région, inférieur à la moyenne pluriannuelle (10,7 en 2005 contre 11,5 depuis 1993). Cette baisse de qualité est particulièrement perceptible sur la Côte Est Cotentin et en Baie des Veys. Les résultats concernant les infestations par le Polydora sont par contre excellents et 2005 se révèle comme la meilleure année depuis le début de REMONOR par les faibles niveaux d'infestation observés</dc:description>
  <dc:date>2006-11</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Report</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/2006/rapport-2212.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:language>fr</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/2212/</dc:relation>
</oai_dc:dc>