<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Competition for food in the larvae of two marine molluscs, Crepidula fornicata and Crassostrea gigas</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Blanchard, Michel</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Pechenik, J</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Giudicelli, E</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Connan, Jean-paul</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Robert, Rene</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>Larvae, Crepidula fornicata, Crassostrea gigas</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Growth</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Feeding rate</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Diet</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Phytoplankton</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>The degree to which larvae of the invasive American slipper limpet (Crepidula fornicata) and the Japanese oyster (Crassostrea gigas) may compete for food was examined during 2003 in the laboratory. Larval microalgae uptake, growth and mortality were compared for larvae fed each of six species of unicellular algae, ranging in length from 2 to 10 mu m. Tested diets included the two flagellates Tetraselmis chui (Prasinophyceae) and Isochrysis affinis galbana (T-ISO, Haptophyceae), one member of the Chlorophyceae (Nannochloris atomus), and three diatom species (Chaetoceros calcitrans forma pumilum, Chaetoceros gracilis, Skeletonema marino). We found that the limpet larvae ingested phytoplankton over a wider range of cell sizes and ate at higher rates on each diet than did the oyster larvae. For example, oyster larvae consumed 2216 cells h(-1) of N. atomus, while limpet larvae consumed the same phytoplankton cells at approximately twice that rate, 5159 cells h(-1), on the same diet. Larvae of both species grew more quickly on a mixture of flagellates than on any of the diatom alone (12 versus 7 mu m d(-1) for oyster larvae and 41 versus 28 mu m d(-1) for limpet larvae). Our results suggest that in the Bay of Mount Saint-Michel (France, Western Channel), where larvae of both species co-exist in the summer, intensive grazing by limpet larvae can potentially deplete phytoplankton concentrations to cause competition with oyster larvae, particularly for smaller sized phytoplankton species.</dc:description>
  <dc:description>Compétition trophique chez les larves de mollusques marins Crepidula fornicata et Crassostrea gigas. En 2003, des expérimentations ont été menées en laboratoire pour évaluer la compétition trophique entre les larves de crépidules (Crepidula fornicata) et celles de l'huître japonaise (Crassostrea gigas). Les taux de consommation,  de croissance et de mortalité sont comparés, en alimentant les larves de chaque mollusque avec six espèces d'algues unicellulaires, dont la taille varie de 2 à 10 &amp;#956;m, deux flagellées Tetraselmis chui (Prasinophycée) et Isochrysis affinis galbana (T-ISO, Haptophycée), une chlorophycée Nannochloris atomus, et trois diatomées : Chaetoceros calcitrans forma pumilum, Chaetoceros gracilis et Skeletonema marinoï. Contrairement aux larves d'huîtres, les larves de crépidules consomment toutes les cellules phytoplanctoniques quelles que soient leurs tailles, et ceci, à un taux plusélevé que celui des larves d'huîtres. Ainsi, une larve d'huître consomme 2216  cellules h&amp;#8722;1 de N. atomus, tandis que la larve de crépidule en consomme 5159 cellules h&amp;#8722;1, soit environ deux fois plus. Ces expériences mettent également en évidence que les larves des deux espèces grandissent plus vite quand elles sont nourries avec le mélange des algues flagellées plutôt qu'avec chacune des espèces de ces mêmes algues (12 contre 7 &amp;#956;m j&amp;#8722;1 pour l'huître et 41 contre 28 &amp;#956;m j&amp;#8722;1 pour la crépidule). Ainsi, en baie du Mont Saint-Michel (Manche ouest) où les larves des deux espèces apparaissent à la même période estivale, nos résultats suggèrent que la filtration des larves de crépidules abaisse notablement la concentration de phytoplancton, et tout spécialement celle des petites cellules algales, entraînant alors une compétition trophique avec les larves d'huîtres.</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>EDP Sciences</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>2008-04</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Publication</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/2008/publication-4703.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:identifier>DOI:10.1051/alr:2008025</dc:identifier>
  <dc:source>Aquatic Living Resources (0990-7440) (EDP Sciences), 2008-04 , Vol. 21 , N. 2 , P. 197-205</dc:source>
  <dc:language>en</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/4703/</dc:relation>
  <dc:rights>EDP Sciences, IFREMER, IRD 2008</dc:rights>
</oai_dc:dc>