<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Dynamique et enzymologie de la digestion chez l'huitre Crassostrea gigas</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Boucaud, C</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Lebesnerais, C</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Lubet, P</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Lihrmann, I</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>Crassostrea gigas</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Bivalvia</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Cytology</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Histochemistry</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Histology</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Digestive system</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Enzymatic activity</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Digestive glands</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Digestion</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Enzymes</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Transit digestif</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Digestion</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Huitre</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Crassostrea gigas</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>Feeding experiments carried out on Crassostrea gigas allowed the authors to set up the stages and the timing of the movement of food throughout the digestive tract. Various activities involved in digestion (glycosidases, esterases, and peptidases) were investigated histochemically in the digestive tract in order to localize the sites of absorption and the sites of protein and carbohydrate digestion. An explicative model of the different stages of digestion is proposed.</dc:description>
  <dc:description>Chez Crassostrea gigas (Thunberg) des expériences d'alimentation contrôlée ont permis d'établir les modalités et la chronologie du transit alimentaire. Différentes activités enzymatiques en relation avec la digestion (glycosidases, esterases et peptidases) ont été localisées dans l'appareil digestif et ont permis de préciser les sites de digestion des glucides et des protides et les sites d'absorption. Un schéma explicatif des différentes étapes de la digestion est proposé.</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>Actes de colloques. Ifremer. Brest [ACTES COLLOQ. IFREMER.]. 1985</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>1983-12</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Conference article</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/1983/acte-1179.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:language>fr</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/1179/</dc:relation>
</oai_dc:dc>