<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Simulation de la dynamique de pêcherie : modélisation, complexité et incertitude</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Mahevas, Stephanie</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>Statistics</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Spatial</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Management</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Optimal complexity</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Sensitivity</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>ISIS Fish</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>statistiques</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>spatial</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>gestion</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>complexité optimale</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>sensibilité</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>ISIS Fish</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>Fisheries are defined by a set of fishermen and of marine populations impacting each other in a spatial-limited marine ecosystem. Within the over-exploitation context and according to ratified sustainable management objectives, my research has been focused on the development and a caution use of a mechanistic model describing fisheries dynamics. This model allows for integrating existing knowledge of fisheries. It aims at improving the understanding of fisheries functioning and at investigating the impact of fishing regulations on fisheries dynamics. This modelling exercise has supported many methodological developments for its parametrisation and its use in uncertainty context. Concerned with promoting a correct use of a complex model (that ambiguity link to numerous uncertainties could lead to an instrumental use of models moving beyond the scientific framework), I have been interested in a statistical approach of sensitivity analysis. The first part of my manuscript describes the fisheries dynamics model ISIS-Fish (Integration of Spatial Information for Simulation of Fisheries) and its use for several case-studies. The second part focus on statistical methods to estimate model's parameters. Finally, in the third part I present some developments on sensitivity analysis to take into account for inputs uncertainty on simulation outputs. I conclude by giving some perspectives of my work.</dc:description>
  <dc:description>Une pêcherie est un ensemble de pêcheurs et de populations marines s'impactant mutuellement dans un écosystème marin géographiquement délimité. Dans un contexte de sur-pêche des populations marines et de ratification d'objectifs de gestion durable des pêcheries et écosystèmes marins, mon activité s'est centrée sur le développement et l'utilisation contrôlée d'un modèle mécaniste décrivant la dynamique de pêcherie. Ce modèle intégrateur de la connaissance a pour objectif d'aider à la compréhension du fonctionnement des pêcheries et d'évaluer par simulation l'impact de différentes réglementations de la pêche. L'élaboration de ce modèle et de l'outil de simulation qui en résulte ont été un support à de nombreux développements méthodologiques visant à sa paramétrisation et son usage dans un contexte d'incertitude. Soucieuse d'une utilisation honnête d'un modèle complexe qui de part les nombreuses incertitudes peut être source d'ambiguïté que tout un chacun peut s'approprier à des fins pouvant se détourner du cadre scientifique je me suis intéressée aux méthodes statistiques d'analyses de sensibilité. La première partie de mon manuscrit décrit le modèle de dynamique de pêcherie ISIS-Fish (Integration of Spatial Information for Simulation of Fisheries) et son application à plusieurs cas d'étude. La deuxième partie se concentre sur le développement de méthodes d'estimation des paramètres du modèle. Enfin la troisième partie est dédiée au développement d'analyses de sensibilité pour prendre en compte l'impact des incertitudes sur les sorties d'un modèle de simulation. Je conclus en introduisant un certain nombre de perspectives de travail.</dc:description>
  <dc:date>2009-06-12</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>HDR</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/2009/these-7302.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:language>fr</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/7302/</dc:relation>
</oai_dc:dc>