<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Methods for microbial biomass, community structure and metabolic activities on surfaces.</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>White, D</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>Bacteria</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Fouling</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Bioassays</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Metabolism</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Surfaces</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Bacteria collecting devices</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Culture media</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Microbiological analysis</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>Microbes in nature are often concentrated on surfaces where they exist in microcolonies of mixed composition. The assay of these mixed microbial consortia by utilizing biochemical components eliminates the problems associated with cultural selectivity of viable counts or the requirement for quantitative release from surfaces required in some microscopic techniques. The assay of cellular components restricted to subsets of the microbial community gives insights into the community structure of the biofilm whereas assay of cellular components common to all cells can be used for biomass estimations. Formation of endogenous storage materials can be utilized as measures of nutritional status and rates of formation or turnover of specific "signatures" from labeled precursors can give insight into metabolic activities. Extracellular polymers involved in adhesion are also important components of biofilms. These analyses are destructive. They can now be correlated with non-destructive analyses by Fourier transforming infrared spectrometry which may provide real-time analyses of biofilm dynamics.</dc:description>
  <dc:description>Les bactéries en milieu naturel sont souvent concentrées sur des surfaces où elles existent en microcolonies de composition variée. I.'étude de ces populations microbiennes mixtes par l'utilisation de composants biochimiques élimine les problèmes liés à la sélectivité des milieux de culture pour la numération des bactéries viables ou encore les problèmes liés à l'obligation de décrocher quantitativement les microorganismes fixés aux surfaces pour certaines techniques de microscopie. L'étude des composants cellulaires caractéristiques donne un aperçu sur la structure de la communauté du biofilm alors que l'étude des composants cellulaires communs à toutes les cellules peut servir, elle, à des estimations de biomasse. La formation de réserves endogènes peut être utilisée pour mesurer l'état nutritionnel. Le taux de formation ou turn-over de signatures spécifiques à partir de précurseurs marqués peut apporter des informations sur leurs activités métaboliques. Les polymères extracellulaires ayant un rôle dans l'adhésion sont également d'importants composants du biofilm Mais leur analyse les détruit. Cependant elle peut maintenant être comparée aux analyses non destructives en spectrophotométrie infrarouge à transformée de Fourier, qui apporte des renseignements en temps réel sur la dynamique du biofilm.</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>Actes de colloques. Ifremer Brest [ACTES COLLOQ. IFREMER.]. 1986</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>1984-10</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Conference article</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/1984/acte-963.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:language>en</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/963/</dc:relation>
</oai_dc:dc>