<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Contribution à l'étude des cumaces de profondeur de l'atlantique nord : le genre Makrokylindrus Stebbing)</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Reyss, Daniel</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>Histoire Ifremer</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>The genus Makrokylindrus Stebbing, 1912, is characteristic of deep waters, since, out of the 32 species know to this day, only two, M. serricaudata (Scott, 1912) and M. fistularis (Calman, 1911), have been collected at depths of less than 200 m. The study of collections from previous cruises in the North Atlantic Ocean enabled us to identify some of the 11 species already known in this area and to complete the inventory of this genus by describing 7 new species. The studied material comes from the following cruises: - Noratlante cruise (R.S. "Jean Charcot", August-September-October 1969) of the Brittany Oceanology Centre (NOR). - cruises by H. L. Sanders (Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution) on board the "Gay Head- Bermuda transect", 1960-1969 (BER). - cruise of the "Sarsia" in the Bay of Biscay, July 1967, (GAS). - cruise of the "Discovery" in the Canaries, March 1968 (CAN).</dc:description>
  <dc:description>Le genre Makrokylindrus Stebbing, 1912, est caractéristique des eaux profondes, puisque, sur les 32 espèces connues à ce jour, deux seulement, M. serricaudata (Scott, 1912) et M. fistularis (Calman, 1911), ont été récoltées à une profondeur inférieure à 200 m.  L'étude de quelques collections provenant de campagnes en Atlantique nord a permis de retrouver quelques unes des 11 espèces qui y étaient déjà connues et de compléter l'inventaire du genre par la description de 7 espèces nouvelles.  Le matériel étudié provient des campagnes suivantes:  - campagne Noratlante (N.O. Jean Charcot, août-septembre-octobre 1969) du Centre Océanologique de Bretagne (NOR).  - campagnes de H. L. Sanders (Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution) sur le ,,Gay Head- Bermuda transect", 1960-1969 (BER).  - campagne de la ,,Sarsia" dans le Golfe de Gascogne, juillet 1967, (GAS).  - campagne du Discovery aux Canaries, mars 1968 (CAN). [OCR NON CONTRÔLE]</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>Leiden. E.J. BRILL</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>1974</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Publication</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/1974/publication-5116.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:source>Crustaceana (Leiden. E.J. BRILL), 1974 , Vol. 26 , N. 1 , P. 5-28</dc:source>
  <dc:language>fr</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/5116/</dc:relation>
  <dc:rights>Leiden. E.J. BRILL</dc:rights>
</oai_dc:dc>