<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Stockage et transport des crustacés vivants</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Chartois, Herve</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Latrouite, Daniel</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Le Carre, P</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>Lobsters</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Crabs</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Shellfish</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Survival rate</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Transport</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Storage</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Crustacean</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Fishery products</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Langoustes</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Homards</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Crabes</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Physiologie</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Survie</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Transport</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Stockage</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Crustacés</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>Fishing and trade of living crustaceans are dynamic commercial sectors in France. 25 000  tons of local or imported crabs, lobsters , crawsfishes are yearly treated. Based upon a literature review and fishmongers interviews, this study  describes the current pratices and problems associated to live crabs and  lobsters storage. Supply conditions of live crustaceans, marketing  networks, and biological, ecological and physiological characteristics of crustaceans were discussed. Morever, storage facilities, their  operating rules and factors affecting the survival rate under storage  and transportation conditions were reviewed.</dc:description>
  <dc:description>Cette étude, qui repose sur des analyses bibliographiques et des enquêtes auprès des mareyeurs, expose les pratiques et les contraintes du stockage des crustacés vivants. Elle traite successivement des conditions d'approvisionnement en crabes, homards et langoustes, des circuits commerciaux, des caractéristiques biologiques et écologiques de ces espèces, de certains aspects de leur physiologie, des installations de stockage et de leur principe de fonctionnement, puis des facteurs qui affectent la survie des crustacés lors du stockage et du transport.</dc:description>
  <dc:date>1994-05</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Report</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/1994/rapport-634.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:language>fr</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/634/</dc:relation>
</oai_dc:dc>