<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Transit bacterien dans le tube digestive de la truite arc-en-ciel</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Lesel, R</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Fauconneau, B</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Alzieu, P</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>Citrobacter freundii</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Bacillus stearothermophilus</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Bacteria</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Excretion</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Tracer techniques</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>The present study concerns bacterial transit in the digestive tract of rainbow trout at 13 degree C and compares fecal excretion of 4 tracers in the alimentary bolus, an inert bacterial tracer: spores of Bacillus stearothermophilus , a bacterial marker capable of multiplying in the digestive organs: Citrobacter freundii ; a tracer of the liquid phase: polyethylene glycol (PEG), a tracer of the solid phase: Cr sub(2)O sub(3). Two peaks of fecal excretion of bacterial bodies are indicated in the results, the first one taking place within the first 4 h following ingestion of the traced meal, the second peak, a hundred times more important, occurring 10 h after the meal. This two-phase mode of excretion corroborates the observations previously made. The physical tracers (PEG and Cr sub(2)O sub(3)) utilized seem to follow the same pattern of excretion, in spite of a lesser sensitivity. They show the existence of an early faecal excretion. A high number of pyloric caeca does not seem to involve modifications of the digestive transit speed. These results show interest in bacteria as markers of liquid and solid phases in the alimentary bolus.</dc:description>
  <dc:description>Cette étude a pour objet le transit des bactéries dans le tube digestif de la truite arc-en-ciel à 13°Cet l'excrétion fécale comparée de 4 marqueurs dans le bol alimentaire, un marqueur bactérien inerte : spores de Bacillus siearoihermophilus, un marqueur bactérien susceptible de se multiplier dans les compartiments digestifs : Citrobacterfreundii, un marqueur de la phase liquide: polyethylene glycol (PEG), un marqueur de la phase solide, Cr2C&gt;3. L'analyse montre qu'il existe deux pics d'excrétion bactérienne fécale : le premier a lieu dans les 4 premières heures qui suivent l'ingestion du repas marqué, le second pic, cent fois plus important, se produit 10 heures après le repas. Cette excrétion bimodale corrobore les observations précédentes. Les marqueurs physiques utilisés (PEG et Cr2Û3) paraissent suivre un mode d'excrétion analogue, malgré une sensibilité moindre. Ils indiquent l'existence d'une excrétion fécale précoce. La présence d'un nombre élevé de caeca pyloriques ne paraît pas induire de modification sensible de la vitesse du transit digestif. Ces résultats montrent l'intérêt des bactéries comme marqueurs des phases liquide et solide du bol alimentaire.</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>Actes de colloques. Ifremer Brest [ACTES COLLOQ. IFREMER.]. 1986</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>1984-10</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Conference article</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/1984/acte-995.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:language>fr</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/995/</dc:relation>
</oai_dc:dc>