<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Métabolisme de l'huître Crassostrea gigas stockée dans des dégorgeoirs conchylicoles, à différentes densités et saisons</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Bougrier, Serge</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Masson, Daniel</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Geairon, Philippe</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Fouche, Dominique</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Leroy, Anne</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Faury, Nicole</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Ratiskol, Jacqueline</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>Physiology</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Oyster farmers</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Crassostrea gigas</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Oysters</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Storage tanks</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Physiologie</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Ostréiculture</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Dégorgeoirs</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Crassostrea gigas</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Huîtres</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Bassin stockage</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>One of the problems faced by oyster farmers in France is the immediate or delayed mortality of oysters in the storage tanks prior to shipping. This may be due to overstocking and/or improper water management. To investigate the problem, experiments were performed in commercial storage tanks stocked with oysters at different densities. The aim of this study was to provide some basic experimental data and guidelines for better handling of oysters prior to shipping</dc:description>
  <dc:description>En France, avant commercialisation, les coquillages doivent séjourner dans des bassins de stockage. Une mauvaise gestion de l'eau et/ou une charge importante peuvent engendrer des mortalités, parfois massives. Le but de cette étude est d'acquérir des données de base pour à terme fournir des recommandations sur la gestion des bassins de stockage. Pour cela, des populations d'huîtres ont été stockées dans des dégorgeoirs, comparables à ceux des professionnels, à différentes densités et à trois saisons.</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>Counc. Meet. of the Int. Counc. for the Exploration of the Sea, La Rochelle (France), 26 Sep-4 Oct 1991</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>1991-09-24</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Conference article</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/1991/acte-3047.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:language>fr</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/3047/</dc:relation>
</oai_dc:dc>