<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Survie des langoustines (Nephrops norvegicus ) s'echappant d'un cul de chalut</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Morizur, Yvon</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Charuau, Anatole</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Rivoalen, Jean-jacques</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>size distribution</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>crustacean fisheries</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>mesh selectivity</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>trawling</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>fishing mortality</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>survival</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>The survival rate of Nephrops escaping through the cod-end was recently studied in the Bay of Biscay. Over the 45mm meshed cod-end was put a 15mm meshed net in order to retain the Nephrops escaping though, the cod-end. Soon after hauling escaped Nephrops were returned on the sea-bed into cages. After an inversion of 60-78 hours, the average survived rate was about 70 %. However it was found increasing with the size of individuals. The value obtained, which is only a result of- the action oh several factors, may be lower than the true value. I he evolution, of this biological parameter according to the mesh size is discussed in the scope of assessments</dc:description>
  <dc:description>Le taux de survie des langoustines s'échappant à travers les mailles d'un cul de chalut a été étudié dans le Golfe de Gascogne. Sur le cul de chalut muni d'un maillage de 45 mm a été ajoutée une double-pêche en un maillage de 15mm: afin de recueillir les langoustines échappées. Les langoustines ainsi retenues ont été ré immergées dans des casiers. Après une immersion de 60-78 heures, le taux ce survie moyen était de l'ordre de 70%- Le taux de survie augmente avec la taille ces individus. Le taux de survie moyen obtenu n'est qu'une résultante de divers facteurs. Cette résultante pourrait dans le cas présent, être un minorant. L'évolution de ce paramètre biologique en fonction de la taille des vailles est, en outre, discutée.</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>ICES-CM-1982/B:14</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>1982</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Conference article</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/1982/acte-2339.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:language>fr</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/2339/</dc:relation>
</oai_dc:dc>