<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>La maladie de la glande digestive d'Ostrea edulis Linne</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Grizel, Henri</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Tige, Gilbert</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>Glande digestive</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Maladie</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Ostrea edulis</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Huître</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Pathologie</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>The first microscope observations of the digestive gland of Ostrea edulis were conducted by Comps (1970) and Herbach (1971), but the first effects had already been observed in the autumn of 1967. During summer 1968, an abnormal mortality occurred in the upstream part of the Aber Wrach, then spread downstream and into the Aber Benoît. Similar mortalities were also observed in the area of La Tremblade and in the Arcachon Bay. Since then, a permanent monitoring is conducted in the different Breton oyster culture centres and the Arcachon area.</dc:description>
  <dc:description>Les premières observations microscopiques concernant la maladie de la glande digestive d'Ostrea edulis furent faites par COMPS (1970) et HERBACH (1971), mais les premiers effets avaient déjà été notés au cours de l'automne 1967. Durant l'été 1968, une mortalité anormale survint dans la partie amont de l'Aber Wrach, puis s'étendit vers la partie aval et dans l'Aber Benoît. De telles mortalités ont été constatées aussi dans la région de La Tremblade et dans le bassin d'Arcachon. Depuis un contrôle permanent est effectué dans les différents centres ostréicoles bretons et dans la région d'Arcachon.</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>Actes CIEM, CM 1973/K:13</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>1973</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Conference article</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/1973/acte-5929.PDF</dc:identifier>
  <dc:language>fr</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/5929/</dc:relation>
</oai_dc:dc>