<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Impact de la salmoniculture marine sur l'environnement en rade de Cherbourg (1993-1995) 2. étude biosédimentaire</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Kempf, Marc</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Cadour, Gwenael</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Jeanneret, Hélène</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Mear, Yan</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Miramand, Pierre</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Merceron, Michel</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>France</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Cherbourg</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>benthos</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>sediment</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>environmental impact</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>trout</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Marine fish farming</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>rade de Cherbourg</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>étude biosédimentaire</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>impact</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Salmoniculture marine</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>This document is a result of an environmental impact study carried out between 1993 and 1995 on the site of a marine trout culture located in the Harbour of Cherbourg, France. It deals with the solid waste of the farm and concems deposition rate, sediment analysis and chemistry (fine fraction &lt; 63 ~m, organic matter, carbon, nitrogen, copper and zinc), bottom living organisms and underwater video monitoring. The impact observed is very moderate and localised. This is mainly due to the strong d)'TIamics and flushing rate of the site.
A seperate volume of the same study deals with dissolved waste and concems the water mass (volume 1 : water and pelagos).
(Not controlled OCR)</dc:description>
  <dc:description>Ce document constitue la synthèse de l'étude biosédimentaire réalisée, entre 1993 et 1995, sur le site d'élevage salmonicole de la rade de Cherbourg afin d'en estimer les impacts. Il s'intéresse aux rejets solides et regroupe l'analyse du flux de matières, de la géochimie du sédiment (fraction fine &lt; 63 ~m, matière organique, carbone, azolte, cuivre et zinc), de la faune benthique ainsi qu'un suivi vidéo. Ses conclusions sont que la rade ne subit qu'un impact relativement faible, localisé et temporaire en provenance de l'élevage piscicole et ce, notamment, en raison d'une forte d)'TIamique.
Un volume distinct du même travail a été consacré aux effluents liquides et à la masse d'eau (volume l, eau et pelagos).
(OCR non controlé)</dc:description>
  <dc:date>1997-05</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Report</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/1997/rapport-3349.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:language>fr</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/3349/</dc:relation>
</oai_dc:dc>