<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Surveillance Écologique et Halieutique. Site de Gravelines. Novembre 2006 - Octobre 2007</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Lefebvre, Alain</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Antajan, Elvire</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Delesmont, R</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Dewarumez, J. M.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Luczak, C</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>Benthos</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Microbiology</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Plankton</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Fisheries</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Hydrology</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Network survey</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Gravelines</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Nuclear power plant</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Benthos</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Microbiologie</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Plancton</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Halieutique</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Hydrologie</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Surveillance</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Gravelines</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Centrale nucléaire</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>This is the 30th annual surveillance report concerning the central nuclear power plant of Gravelines. This very high power level results from six plant units located on the shore and is characterised by a cooling system with a coastal surface input and output. The production of electricity began in 1980  and reached maximum in 1986. Surveillance studies concern monitoring of fish populations (larvae and eggs of Sole and Sprat) or crustaceans (shrimps), benthic system (intertidal and subtidal) and pelagic system (hydrology, microbiology, phytoplancton, zooplancton). This survey deals with spatial and temporal approaches (i) study of the direct impact by comparison of the input and output seawater stations, (ii) study of medium and long term evolution of the area by comparison with a reference station.</dc:description>
  <dc:description>Ce travail constitue le 30e rapport de surveillance du site électronucléaire de Gravelines dont la grande puissance est assurée par le fonctionnement de 6 tranches. Ce site, implanté sur le littoral, présente une prise d'eau de mer assurant le refroidissement du système et un rejet côtier d'eau chaude en surface. Le fonctionnement de la centrale a débuté en 1980 et elle a atteint la puissance maximale en 1986. La surveillance concerne le milieu halieutique (larves et oeufs de Sole, de Sprat et crevettes grises), les milieux benthiques (intertidal et subtidal) et pélagique  (hydrologie, microbiologie,phytoplancton, zooplancton). La stratégie de surveillance est basée sur une approche spatiale et temporelle (i) Etude de l'impact immédiat par comparaison de la station «Prise d'eau» et de la station «Canal de rejet» sur une surface limitée (ii) Etude de l'évolution à moyen ou à long terme du milieu marin par rapport à une situation de référence (échelle locale).</dc:description>
  <dc:date>2008-03</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Report</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/2008/rapport-4007.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:language>fr</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/4007/</dc:relation>
</oai_dc:dc>