<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Aquaculture 1974</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Laubier, Lucien</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>Histoire Ifremer</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>Started in 1967, the first five-year research programme of the C.N.E.X.O. deals with non conventional sea-farming, i.e. the developement of new types of marine organisms breeding. These works are conducted in tight connexion with some industrialists and University laboratories, contracting parties of the C.N.E.X.O. The research has dealt simultaneously with molluscs (5 species), crustacea (4 species) and fishes (4 species). The tests made on scallops (in Brest and St-Brieuc) should lead to a practical application in 1975. It seems that those concerning the ear-shell will have in a short time a large scale application (like in Japan). Among the 4 crustacea studied, the prawn shrimp appears to be the most interesting. The studies made on the sea wolf and the chrysophys are full of promise. The reproduction of turbot remains difficult but its growth is remarkable and this artificially bred fish does not need any special food ; it is hoped that turbot breeding will increase. [NOT CONTROLLED OCR]</dc:description>
  <dc:description>Lancé en 1967, le premier programme quinquennal de recherches du C.N.E.X.O. concerne l'aquaculture non traditionnelle, c'est-à-dire la promotion de nouvelles formes d'élevage d'organismes marins, travaux effectués en liaison intime avec des industriels et certains laboratoires universitaires, contractants du C.N.E.X.O. Les recherches ont porté simultanément sur des mollusques (5 espèces), des crustacés (4 espèces), des poissons (4 espèces). Les expériences sur la coquille St-Jacques (à Brest et St-Brieuc) devraient déboucher en 1975 sur une application pratique. Celles qui concernent l'ormeau paraissent proches d'une application à grande échelle (comme au Japon). Des 4 crustacés étudiés, la crevette bouquet semble la plus intéressante. Les travaux sur le bar et la daurade sont prometteurs. Pour le turbot la reproduction est encore délicate mais la croissance est remarquable et ce poisson d'élevage n'est pas très exigeant quant à son alimentation ; on peut donc espérer voir se développer des élevages de turbot. [OCR NON CONTRÔLE]</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>Institut Français de la Mer</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>1974</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Publication</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/1974/publication-5457.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:source>La revue maritime (Institut Français de la Mer), 1974 , N. 297 , P. 419-436</dc:source>
  <dc:language>fr</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/5457/</dc:relation>
  <dc:rights>Institut Français de la Mer</dc:rights>
</oai_dc:dc>