<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Influence of the diet on the microbial diversity of faecal and gastrointestinal contents in gilthead sea bream (Sparus aurata) and intestinal contents in goldfish (Carassius auratus)</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>De Paula Silva, Flavia Cristina</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Nicoli, Jacques Robert</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Zambonino, Jose Luiz</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Kaushik, Sadasivam</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Gatesoupe, François-joel</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>Vegetable meals</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>DGGE</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>microbiota</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>stomach</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>intestine</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>faeces</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>Fish intestinal microbiota changes with diet and this effect is of particular interest considering the increasing substitution of fish meal by plant protein sources. The objective of this work was to study the effects of partial substitution of fish meal with lupin and rapeseed meals on gut microbiota of the gilthead sea bream (Sparus aurata) and in goldfish (Carassius auratus). Faecal, gastrointestinal and intestinal contents were characterized by culture-based and molecular methods. Vibrionaceae was high in faeces and in the intestine of sea bream, while a more diverse microbiota was retrieved from the stomach, where Bacillales and Flavobacteriaceae appeared to be influenced by the diet. PCR-DGGE profiles revealed high diversity of the microbiota transiting in the sea bream digestive tract, with a shift between gastric and intestinal communities, specially in the group fed with lupin meal. The goldfish was different, with predominance of Aeromonas spp., Shewanella putrefaciens and Staphylococcus spp. among the aerotolerant cultivable bacteria. The culture-independent methods revealed the presence of anaerobes like Cetobacterium somerae, and that of Vibrio spp., likely in a viable but non-cultivable state. There was a trend towards decreasing diversity in goldfish microbiota with the partial substitution by lupin, which seemed to inhibit some taxa.</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>Wiley-blackwell</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>2011-11</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Publication</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00040/15096/12440.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:identifier>DOI:10.1111/j.1574-6941.2011.01155.x</dc:identifier>
  <dc:source>Fems Microbiology Ecology (0168-6496) (Wiley-blackwell), 2011-11 , Vol. 78 , N. 2 , P. 285-296</dc:source>
  <dc:language>en</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00040/15096/</dc:relation>
  <dc:rights>2011 Wiley / Blackwell</dc:rights>
</oai_dc:dc>