<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Influence of hydrolysis time on protein recovery and amino acid composition of hydrolysates from Sepia officinalis viscera</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Soufi-kechaou, Emna</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Jaouen, Pascal</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Ben Amar, Raja</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Berge, Jean-pascal</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>Enzymatic hydrolysis</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Cuttlefish Protein Hydrolysates (CPH)</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Cuttlefish By-Products (CBP)</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Essential Amino Acids (EAA)</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Protein recovery</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>Enzymatic hydrolysis of cuttlefish viscera by Protamex, Pepsin, Delvolase and Multifect Neutral was investigated in a batch reactor during 6 hours with an hourly sampling. The influence of the enzyme used and the hydrolysis conditions (operating pH, temperature) was studied with regards to the extent of proteolytic degradation and to molecular weight distribution of the peptides. After 360 min of hydrolysis, cuttlefish viscera treated with Pepsin yielded significantly (p &lt; 0.05) higher protein recoveries compared to the substrate autolysed or treated with other external proteases. However, the amino acid composition showed that this was Protamex hydrolysis which gave the highest percentage of essential amino acids. At least, according to the FPLC patterns, the cuttlefish protein hydrolysates (CPH) were rich in low-molecular-weight peptides, especially with Protamex and Pepsin.</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>RUT Printer and Publisher Jalna (MS) India</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>2012-04</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Publication</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00114/22508/20191.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:source>Science Research Reporter (2249-2321) (RUT Printer and Publisher Jalna (MS) India), 2012-04 , Vol. 2 , N. 2 , P. 115-129</dc:source>
  <dc:language>en</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00114/22508/</dc:relation>
  <dc:rights>RUT Printer and Publisher, Jalna (MS) India, Designed by Dr. Umesh P. Mogle Chief Editor</dc:rights>
</oai_dc:dc>