<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Altimetry and models in the tropical oceans - a review</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Arnault, S</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Perigaud, C</dc:creator>
  <dc:description>Tropical oceans play a key role in climatic variations. Ocean-atmosphere interactions induce large-scale and low-frequency variations which, due to the specificity of tropical ocean dynamics, are very difficult to observe with traditional in situ measurements. During the past twenty years, a variety of numerical models of diverse complexity have contributed much to the description, understanding and prediction of ocean variability in the tropics. However, the capacity of these models to simulate adequately the ocean variability heavily depends on the accuracy of the atmospheric forcings and that of initial conditions. Satellite altimetry provides a unique opportunity to avoid the problem of scarce and non-synoptic in situ data coverage for the large-scale low-frequency monitoring of the tropical oceans. Preliminary results have been obtained with Geos 3 and Seasat altimeter data acquired in the late 1970s. The most recent demonstration of such a capacity is the multi-year Geosat mission of the late 1980s. However the use.of the sea level variations monitored by Geosat for ocean description is severely limited by the lack of accuracy of the mission dedicated to geodesy. Such a limitation will no longer exist after the launch in 1992 of the Topex-Poseidon satellite which is dedicated to oceanography. Nonetheless these future satellite observations will not alone be sufficient to determine, for example, the oceanic transport of heat involved in climatic variations: it is in the combination of numerical models and altimetry that answers to such a question may lie. Data assimilation into numerical models is a fairly new adventure for oceanographers, the few examples of assimilation of actual altimetric data in the tropics being of very recent date. Different methods have been applied in these examples with different objectives of assimilation, indicating a variety of directions for future research in what is a promising field.</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>Gauthier-Villars</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>1992</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Publication</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00100/21174/18791.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:source>Oceanologica Acta (0399-1784) (Gauthier-Villars), 1992 , Vol. 15 , N. 5 , P. 411-430</dc:source>
  <dc:language>en</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00100/21174/</dc:relation>
</oai_dc:dc>