<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Attendrissement enzymatique de chair de mollusques</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Kouadio Kouakou, François</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>Glycymeris glycymeris</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Buccinum undatum</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>texture</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>attendrissement</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>enzyme</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Glycymeris glycymeris. Buccinum undatum</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>texture</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>tenderizing</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>enzyme.</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>Two types of marine molluscs were studied. The highly individual characteristics of the flesh of these two shellfish, in this case its firmness, led us to analyse the behaviour of the foot muscle, the firmest part, as a function of heat and to the determination of the different temperatures at which the denaturation of the main constituent proteins occurs. This firmness makes the muscles difficult to chew to such an extent that they have acted as a break to consumption. 
These shell-fish have very similar proportions of myofibrillar and connective proteins, both of- which are responsible for the texture of meat. This similarity of composition determined the choice of an enzymatic preparation (protease V100) capable of acting simultaneously on both these types of proteins. The canning production tests using these shell-fish gave satisfactory results for Buccinum undatum (whelk) 
With Glycymeris glycymeris (Dog Cockle), two distinct cases were revealed. In medium-sized specimens or those with few intestines, satisfactory tenderizing of the flesh was observed in the canned product. However, the difficulties relating to the size of the intestines in specimens in periods of sexual maturation could not be overcome.</dc:description>
  <dc:description>Deux espèces de mollusques marins ont été étudiées. La caractéristique très particulière de la chair de ces deux coquillages en 1'occurence sa fermeté nous a amenés à analyser le comportement du muscle du pied, la partie la plus ferme, en fonction de la chaleur et à déterminer les différentes températures de dénaturation des protéines constitutives majeures. Cette fermeté rend les muscles difficiles à mastiquer si bien qu'elle constitue un frein à la consommation. Ces coquillages présentent des proportions assez voisines de protéines myofibrillaires et conjonctives, toutes deux responsables de la texture des viandes. Cette composition simillaire a déterminé le choix d'une préparation enzymatique, la protéase V100, capable d'agir à la fois sur les deux types de protéines, les essais de production de conserves à partir de ces coquillages ont donné des résultats satisfaisants pour Buccinum undatum (bulot). Avec Glycymeris glycymeris (amande de mer) deux situations ont été distinguées. Chez les individus de taille moyenne ou comportant peu de viscères, un attendrissement satisfaisant de la chair a été observé sur les conserves. En revanche, des difficultés liées à l'importance des viscères chez les individus en période de maturation sexuelle n'ont pu être surmontées.</dc:description>
  <dc:date>1989</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Report</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00030/14134/11381.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:language>fr</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00030/14134/</dc:relation>
</oai_dc:dc>