<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Etangs solaires à stratification de densité</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Hyacinthe, Jean-louis</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>Histoire Ifremer</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>In this schema of solar ponds, a limited shallow marine area overlays a dark layer where the solar radiation is absorbed. The interna1 thermal convection phenomenon due to heating is cancelled by the action of an adequate vertical density gradient created by salt dissolving. This gradient has to be kept up against the saline dif fusion. Previous experimentation, in Israël for the main, had shown that, after a long enough period of transition to normal running, high temperatures on the bottom of the order of 90°c, can be obtained. CNEXO, the French National Center for the Exploitation of the Ocean, is interested in trying to transform isolated marine natural areas into solar ponds with power order of 100 kW. An experimentation has been launched to specify technical feasability and economical rentability of solar ponds, by the use of an artificial solar basin (1 000 m² area) set up near Montpellier , at Palavas les Flots. [NOT CONTROLLED OCR]</dc:description>
  <dc:description>Dans la technique considérée de lagunes solaires une étendue d'eau de faible profondeur utile est limitée par une couche sombre d'absorption du rayonnement, solaire. Le phénomène interne de convection thermique dû à l'échauffement est supprimé par la présence d'un gradient vertical convenable de densité, créé par dissolution de sel et entretenu pour compenser la diffusion. L'expérimentation antérieure, essentiellement Israélienne, a montré, qu'après un temps de mise en régime important, on peut obtenir une température de fond de l'ordre de 90°C.
Le CNEXO veut étudier la possibilité d'utiliser des étendues marines naturelles et isolées, dans une gamme de puissance utile de l'ordre de 100 kW. Il a lancé, en 1976, une expérimentation d'étude de la faisabilité et de la rentabilité de cette technique de lagune solaire, en s'appuyant 2 sur la mise en oeuvre d'un bassin solaire artificiel de 1 000 m² implanté à Palavas les Flots près de Montpellier. [OCR NON CONTRÔLE]</dc:description>
  <dc:date>1977-04</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Report</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/1977/rapport-4852.PDF</dc:identifier>
  <dc:language>fr</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/4852/</dc:relation>
</oai_dc:dc>