<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Diversification de la production conchylicole : cultures de palourdes sur estran (Compte rendu n°3)</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Goulletquer, Philippe</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>Marennes Oléron</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Culture en claire</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Culture sur estran</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Ruditapes philippinarum</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>Since 1984, experiments have been carried out on clam Ruditapes philippinarum foreshore culture, with a one year pond pre-growth. Culture conditions are now well-known: population level with a tide coefficient of around 70 to 80, sediment of silty or fine grain size, sediment stability over the culture period-between the end of April and November. This culture possibility gives way to a diversification of production in the shellfish culture basin of Marennes-Oléron and can be used as an alternative to oyster overexploitation. Clam densities (2 kg/m²) are five times lower than oyster and the Ruditapes philippinarum filtration rate is 20% lower than that of Crassostrea gigas.</dc:description>
  <dc:description>Depuis 1984, des expérimentations portent sur l'élevage de palourdes Ruditapes philippinarum sur estran, prégrossies en claires pendant 1 an. Les conditions d'élevage sont maintenant bien cernées, niveau de la population à un coefficient de l'ordre de 70 à 8O, granulométrie de sédiment sablo-vaseurx ou sableux, stabilité du sédiment sur toute la période d'élevage qui se situe de fin Avril à Novembre. Cette possibilité d'élevage permet une diversification de la production du bassin conchylicole de Marennes-Oléron et peut constituer une alternative à la surexploitation en huîtres. Les densités en palourdes (2 kg/m2) sont cinq fois moins importantes que l'huître et le taux de filtration de Ruditapes philippinarum est inférieur de 20% à celui de Crassostrea gigas.</dc:description>
  <dc:date>1987</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Report</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/1987/rapport-3842.PDF</dc:identifier>
  <dc:language>fr</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/3842/</dc:relation>
</oai_dc:dc>