<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Aspects de conception et de construction d'un bateau d'assaut en composites</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Kader, A</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Yaakob, O</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Samian, Y</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>Malaysia</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Ship technology</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Fibre glass</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Ship design</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Glass reinforced plastics</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Composite materials</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Conception</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Fibre de verre</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Construction</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Bateau d'assaut</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>To help spur the defence industry in Malaysia, the Government is encouraging indigenous research and development effort. This paper describes the development of a prototype fibreglass assault boat at the Universiti Teknologi Malaysia. The boat, designed for riverine and coastal water operations was modelled on aluminium boats currently used by the Malaysian Armed Forces. The completed boat has been evaluated and some minor modifications will be made on the final prototype to be built soon.</dc:description>
  <dc:description>Pour aider l'industrie de la défense à se développer en Malaisie, le gouvernement encourage la recherche et le développement indigène. Cet article décrit le développement d'un prototype de bateau d'assaut en fibre de verre à l'Université de Technologie de Malaisie. Le bateau, conçu pour manoeuvrer dans des eaux fluviales et côtières a été modelé d'après des bateaux en aluminium actuellement en usage dans les forces armées malaises. La totalité du bateau a été évaluée et quelques modifications mineures seront faites sur le prototype final qui sera bientôt en construction.</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>Actes de colloques. Ifremer. Brest [ACTES COLLOQ. IFREMER.]. 1992</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>1992-12</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Conference article</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/1992/acte-1057.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:language>fr</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/1057/</dc:relation>
</oai_dc:dc>