<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Polymorphisme enzymatique de trois populations de palourdes (Ruditapes decussatus L.) de Bretagne</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Moraga, D</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Lucas, A</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>ANE, France, Brittany</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Ruditapes decussatus</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Bivalvia</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Genetics</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Enzymes</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Biopolymorphism</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Bivalve</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Mollusque</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Heterozygotie</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Polymorphisme enzymatique</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>The three populations studied were situated on the west coast of Brittany: to the North (Diben), to the West (Tinduff) to the South (Ile Tudy). 25 to 57 analysis were carried out on each of the 19 enzymatic systems where 27 loci had been recognized. Six of which were not interpreted, 10 were monomorphic, 11 polymorphic. Among these latter, the analysis of 4 of the loci were not used as the determination was too confused. Therefore, the comparison of the 3 populations was carried out on 7 polymorphic loci (EST3, HK2, LAP2, MDH1, MDH2, GPI, PGM2). Only a rare allele showed one qualitative difference; this coupled with slight quantitative differences in the distribution of the alleles did not permit to distinguish the three various populations. The genetic variability of the 3 populations was rather high.</dc:description>
  <dc:description>Les trois populations étudiées étaient localisées sur les côtes de Bretagne Occidentale : au nord (Diben), à l'ouest (Tinduff), au sud (Ile Tudy). De 25 à 57 analyses ont été effectuées sur chacun des 19 systèmes enzymatiques étudiés, où 27 locus ont été reconnus, dont 6 non interprétables, 10 monomorphiques et 11 polymorphiques. Parmi ces derniers, 4 locus ont montré une résolution trop confuse pour que leur analyse soit retenue. C'est donc 7 locus polymorphes (EST3, HK2, LAP2, MDH1,MDH2, GPI, PGM2) qui ont été utilisés pour comparer les 3 populations concernées. Une seule difference qualitative portant sur un allele rare et de très faibles différences quantitatives de distribution des alleles entre les 3 populations, n'ont pas permis de les distinguer. La variabilité génétique des 3 populations est relativement élevée.</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>Actes de colloques. Ifremer. Brest [ACTES COLLOQ. IFREMER.]. 1985</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>1983-12</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Conference article</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/1983/acte-1183.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:language>fr</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/1183/</dc:relation>
</oai_dc:dc>