<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Hydrologie de la Mediterranee occidentale (secteur meridional et Golfe du Lion), en automne 1963 Campagne de la « Thalassa » du 12 octobre au 27 novembre</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Allain, Charles</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Furnestin, Jean</dc:creator>
  <dc:description>The western basin of the Mediterranean was the subject of follow-up hydrological observations during these last few years by ships of the Institute of Maritime Fishing. Knowledge of the thermohaline structure over the far-flung sectors of the coastal strip, that of the fronts that form upon contact with the various opposing masses of water, also that of the particularly active vertical movements in this sea were in fact necessary for attempting to locate the various marine species in their respective habitat. It is in this way that during the summer of 1957, the President Theodore Tissier undertook a campaign that encompasses the sectors of the Alboran Sea, the Catalan Sea, the Gulf of Lion and western Corsica. The results of these observations were published in 1960 by FURNESTIN as regards hydrology, by ALLAIN as regards dynamics. In autumn of the following year, the same ship worked in the entire zone included north of the 42nd parallel, from the Gulf of Lion to the Ligurian Sea (FURNESTIN and ALLAIN, 1962; ALLAIN, 1963).

It was during the winter of 1960 that the President Theodore Tissier performed its last campaign, running along the edge of Algeria up to the 38th parallel (FURNESTIN and ALLAIN, 1962) and, when the Thalassa took over in 1961, two additional sections were carried out, also in winter, between Ivice and western Sardinia, at the 40th parallel and from there to Algiers (FURNESTIN and ALLAIN, 1962).

In the meanwhile, the President Theodore Tissier was able to conduct a special study of the Strait of Gibraltar, focusing on the variations of the hydrological and dynamic regimes during the summer of 1959 (ALLAIN, 1964).

As a follow-up to these campaigns that, carried out in different seasons, already showed the variations that can occur in the hydrological pattern during the year, it was appropriate to study once again, during a transitional period, this zone, which is the southern sector of the western basin, that is directly influenced by the Atlantic current. So it is autumn 1963 that we have chosen to redo normal sections to the Algerian coast and continued up to meridians 38°30 to 39°. An oblique profile, ranging from western Sardinia to the Gulf of Lion allowed us, moreover, to compare our data with those of autumn 1958 in the north of the basin. A special study of the Gulf of Lion was at last undertaken in order to examine the variations that occurred with respect to the results of the two preceding campaigns carried out on this plateau. We will not review the previous research that was cited in preceding publications and to which we will refer during our description of this study.</dc:description>
  <dc:description>Le bassin occidental de la Méditerranée a fait l'objet, au cours de ces dernières années, d'observations hydrologkjues suivies de la part des navires de l'Institut des Pêches maritimes. La connaissance de la structure thermohaline sur les secteurs étendus de la frange littorale, celle des fronts qui se dessinent au contact des différentes masses d'eau en présence, celle aussi des mouvements verticaux particulièrement actifs dans cette mer, nous étaient en effet nécessaires pour essayer de situer les différentes espèces marines dans leur habitat respectif. C'est ainsi que pendant l'été 1957, le « Président Théodore Tissier » entreprenait une campagne englobant les secteurs de la Mer d'Alboran, de la Mer Catalane, du golfe du Lion et de la Corse occidentale. Les résultats de ces observations furent publiés en 1960 par FURNESTIN en ce qui concerne l'hydrologie, par ALLAIN en ce qui traite de la dynamique. L'année suivante, au cours de l'automne, le même navire travaillait dans toute la zone comprise au nord du 42e parallèle, depuis le golfe du Lion jusqu'à la Mer Ligurienne (FURNESTIN et ALLAIN, 1962; ALLAIN, 1963).

C'est pendant l'hiver 1960 que le « Président Théodore Tissier » accomplit sa dernière campagne en parcourant la bordure algérienne jusqu'au 38e parallèle (FURNESTIN et ALLAIN, 1962) et, quand la « Thalassa » prit sa relève en 1961, deux sections complémentaires furent exécutées, en hiver également, entre Ivice et la Sardaigne occidentale, à hauteur du 40e parallèle et de là à Alger (FURNESTIN et ALLAIN, 1962).

Entre temps, le « Président Théodore Tissier » put faire une étude particulière du détroit de Gibraltar, portant sur les variations des régimes hydrologique et dynamique pendant l'été 1959 (ALLAIN, 1964).

Faisant suite à ces campagnes qui. réalisées à des saisons différentes, montraient déjà les variations qui peuvent intervenir au cours de l'année dans la situation hydrologique, il convenait d'étudier à nouveau, pendant une époque de transition, cette zone influencée directement par le courant atlantique qu'est le secteur méridional du bassin occidental. C'est donc l'automne 1963 que nous avons choisi pour refaire des sections normales à la côte algérienne et poussées jusqu'aux méridiens de 38°30 à 39°. Un profil oblique, allant de la Sardaigne occidentale au golfe du Lion, nous a permis, en outre, de comparer nos données à celles de l'automne 1958 dans le N du bassin. Une étude particulière du golfe du Lion fut enfin entreprise pour examiner les variations intervenues par rapport aux résultats des deux campagnes précédentes effectuées sur ce plateau. Nous ne reviendrons pas sur les travaux antérieurs qui ont été cités dans les précédentes publications et auxquels nous nous référerons au cours du développement de cette étude.(OCR non controlé)</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>ISTPM</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>1969-03</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Publication</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/1969/publication-3154.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:source>Revue des Travaux de l'Institut des Pêches Maritimes (0035-2276) (ISTPM), 1969-03 , Vol. 33 , N. 1 , P. 5-78</dc:source>
  <dc:language>fr</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/3154/</dc:relation>
  <dc:rights>Ifremer</dc:rights>
</oai_dc:dc>