<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Comportements cellulaires et régulation génétique au cours des réactions d'immunité innée chez la moule Mytilus galloprovincialis</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Li, Hui</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>Mytilus</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>haemocyte</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>antimicrobial peptides</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>polymorphism</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>genetic regulation</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>innate immunity</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Mytilus</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>hémocyte</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>peptides antimicrobiens</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>polymorphisme</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>régulation génétique</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>immunité innée</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>The mytiliculture is one of the most important aquaculture in the world, however, little is known on the mussel immune system, which plays a critical role in case of infectious diseases. Like all the other invertebrates, our model, the Mediterranean mussel Mytilus galloprovincialis, possesses only an innate immune system considered to be primitive and non-specific. In the present study, our results showed that the mussel immune system (i) is capable of responding differently to a variety of stimulations, suggesting a specific recognition process; (ii) reacts differently according to the geographic origin of the animals, showing an adaptation to their own environment; (iii) is influenced by the season, which explains the seasonal mortalities; (iv) presents an extended polymorphism of antimicrobial peptides, which increases in turn the number of molecular effectors. In conclusion, the innate immunity system of the mussel appears more complex than suspected and involving polymorphic immune effectors. Moreover, this system is capable of responding specifically to different stimuli, of adaptation to the environment, and is influenced by the season.</dc:description>
  <dc:description>La mytiliculture occupe une place très importante dans l'aquaculture, cependant, le système immunitaire de la moule, qui joue un rôle décisif face aux diverses maladies infectieuses, reste mal connu. Comme tous les invertébrés, notre modèle d'étude, la moule méditerranéenne Mytilus galloprovincialis, ne possède qu'un système d'immunité innée souvent décrit comme peu complexe et non spécifique. Les résultats de cette thèse ont montré que le système immunitaire des moules (i) est capable de répondre différemment à diverses stimulations, ce qui suggère une reconnaissance spécifique ; (ii) répond différemment suivant l'origine géographique des animaux, ce qui montre une adaptation à l'environnement ; (iii) est influencé par la saison, ce qui explique les mortalités saisonnières constatées ; (iv) présente un polymorphisme des peptides antimicrobiens, ce qui augmente d'autant le nombre d'effecteurs moléculaires. En conclusion, le système d'immunité innée de la moule apparaît comme complexe, impliquant des effecteurs polymorphes, capable de répondre spécifiquement à divers stimuli, adapté à l'environnement et influencé par la saison.</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>Université de Montpellier 2</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>2008-11-27</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Thesis</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/2008/these-6241.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:language>fr</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/6241/</dc:relation>
</oai_dc:dc>