<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Experimental systems for the study of bacterial degradation of pollutants from the oil industry.</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Wardell, J</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Brown, C</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>Bacteria</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Continuous culture</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Microbiological culture</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Oil and gas industry</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Pollutants</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Pesticides</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Biodegradation</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>The release of pollutants into the environment, either during normal operations or due to accidental discharges, has focussed attention on the fate and effects of xenobiotic compounds in the marine environment. This interest has been heightened by the development of the off-shore industry with the subsequent discharge of biocides from platforms. This paper describes the results obtained from investigations into the fate of biocides in the marine environment using continuous-culture techniques.</dc:description>
  <dc:description>La décharge de polluants, qu'elle soit chronique ou relative à des rejets accidentels, a attiré l'attention sur le devenir et les effets des composés xenobiotiques dans le milieu marin. Cet intérêt a été croissant avec le développement de l'industrie off-shore et les rejets de biocides à partir des plateformes qui ont suivi. Ce papier décrit les résultats obtenus lors de travaux menés en milieu marin sur le devenir de biocides et utilisant les techniques de cultures en continu.</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>Actes de colloques. Ifremer Brest [ACTES COLLOQ. IFREMER.]. 1986</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>1984-10</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Conference article</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/1984/acte-1018.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:language>en</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/1018/</dc:relation>
</oai_dc:dc>