<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Premiers essais d'élevage larvaire de l'ombrine subtropicale (red fish) Sciaenops ocellatus dans les conditions intensives en Martinique</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Soletchnik, Patrick</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Thouard, Emmanuel</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Goyard, Emmanuel</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Baisnee, D</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Baisnee, D</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Baisnee, D</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Yvon, C</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Baker, P</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>French West Indies</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Martinique</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Sciaenops ocellatus</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Larval rearing</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>Two batches of red drum larvae were air shipped from hatcheries in the U.S.A. and stocked in two intensive tank experiments at densities oc 7 :.nd 2-3 larvae per liter. Food items include live rotifers, copepods, brine shrimps. squid and commercial fish pellets. Growth rates were similar in both experiments up to day 20 (12-1" mm) but differences in feeding schedules and an infestation by the dinoflagelate Amyloodinium sp. affected the growth from day 20 to 43 in the second trial. Significant mortalities occurred in the tanks during the first feeding period (days 2 to 7) and again from days 17 to 20 as the result of cannibalism. Survival between day 2 and day 44 was 44% in the first trial. Abnormal inflation of the swim bladder and infection with Amyloodinium sp. reduced the survival to 6-19% in the second.</dc:description>
  <dc:description>Deux lots de larves du tambour rouge ont été transportés par avion depuis des écloseries aux USA et stockés dans deux essais en bac intensif aux densités oc 7 : nd 2-3 larves le litre. L'alimentation comprend les rotifères vivants, les copépodes, les artémias, les encornets et les boulettes de poisson commerciales. Les taux de croissance étaient pareils dans les deux expériences jusqu'au jour 20 (12-1''mm) mais des différences dans les programmes d'alimentation et une infestation par le dinoflagellé Amyloodinium sp. ont modifié la croissance à partir du jour 20 jusqu'au jour 43 dans le deuxième essai. Des mortalités importantes se sont produites dans les bacs pendant la première période d'alimentation (jours 2 et 7) et encore du jour 17 jusqu'au 20 à la suite d'un cannibalisme.  La survie entre le jour 2 et le jour 44 était de 44 % dans le premier essai.  Un gonflement anormal de la vessie natatoire et une infection de l'Amyloodinium sp. ont réduit la survie de 6 ¿ 19 % dans le deuxième.</dc:description>
  <dc:date>1998-09</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Report</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/1998/rapport-1914.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:language>fr</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/1914/</dc:relation>
</oai_dc:dc>