<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Seasonality of internal gravity waves kinetic energy spectra in the Ligurian Basin</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Van Haren, Hans</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Millot, Claude</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>Ligurian Sea</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Kinetic energy spectra</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Internal gravity wave</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Seasonality</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Mer Ligure</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Spectres d'énergie cinétique</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Ondes internes de gravité</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>SeaVariations saisonnières</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>In the central Ligurian Basin, Western Mediterranean Sea, dense water formation occurs in winter so that near-surface stratification displays a marked seasonality. Consequently, kinetic energy spectra from the surface to intermediate depths are entirely different in summer and winter. In summer, the spectra show a peak near the local inertial frequency (f). The polarization of currents in the internal gravity wave frequency (sigma) band (f &lt; sigma &lt; N, N the buoyancy frequency) resembles internal wave theory (for N &gt;&gt;f). In winter, however, no significant near-inertial (or any other) spectral peak is observed and motions are not polarized at any frequencies, whatever the observation depths. With respect to the energy levels observed in summer, those in winter are enhanced at all frequencies (except near f). The seasonal pycnocline determines the summertime development of near-inertial and higher frequency internal waves, also at great depths (similar to 1100 m at least). In winter, no near-surface pycnocline does exist and no (gravity nor gyroscopic) near-inertial internal waves occur; the observed currents are associated with strong mesoscale activity and dense water formation, not with local N. For the 'internal wave band' this implies a lack of scaling of horizontal kinetic energy with N that is reflected in changes of the spectral slope. In the coastal zone of the Ligurian Basin, especially near Corsica, where the alongslope circulation and an almost permanent stratification prevail, near-inertial currents are found yearlong, with only moderate changes in amplitude in the near-surface layer. (</dc:description>
  <dc:description>Dans la partie centrale du bassin ligure (Méditerranée occidentale), un processus de formation d'eau dense se développe en hiver de sorte que la stratification des couches superficielles présente une variabilité saisonnière marquée. En conséquence, les spectres d'énergie cinétique depuis la surface jusqu'à des profondeurs intermédiaires sont très différents entre l'été et l'hiver. En été, les spectres montrent un pic près de la fréquence d'inertie locale (f). La polarisation des courants dans la bande de fréquences (&amp;#963;) des ondes internes de gravité (f &lt; &amp;#963; &lt; N, N étant la fréquence de stabilité) suit la théorie (des ondes internes pour N &gt;&gt; f). En hiver cependant, aucun pic significatif n'apparaît, tant à la fréquence d'inertie qu'à toute autre fréquence, et les courants ne sont polarisés à aucune fréquence, quelle que soit la profondeur d'observation. Par rapport aux niveaux d'énergie observés en été, les niveaux en hiver sont plus importants à toutes les fréquences (sauf f). La pycnocline saisonnière détermine le développement estival d'ondes internes à la fréquence d'inertie et à des fréquences supérieures, jusqu'à des profondeurs relativement grandes (~ 1100 m au moins). En hiver, aucune pycnocline superficielle n'existe et aucune oscillation d'inertie (de gravité ou gyroscopique) n'apparaît ; les courants observés sont associés à une forte activité de moyenne échelle et au processus de formation d'eau dense, pas à N. Ceci implique une absence de relation entre l'énergie cinétique horizontale et N qui se traduit par des changements de la pente des spectres d'énergie dans la bande des ondes internes. Dans les zones côtières du bassin ligure, plus particulièrement près de la Corse, là où la circulation le long de la pente et une stratification quasi-permanente prévalent, des oscillations d'inertie se développent de manière identique tout au long de l'année dans les couches superficielles.</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>Elsevier</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>2003-11</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Publication</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/2003/publication-534.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:identifier>DOI:10.1016/S0399-1784(03)00062-8</dc:identifier>
  <dc:source>Oceanologica Acta (0399-1784) (Elsevier), 2003-11 , Vol. 26 , N. 5-6 , P. 635-644</dc:source>
  <dc:language>en</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/534/</dc:relation>
  <dc:rights>2003 Ifremer/CNRS/IRD. Published by Éditions scientifiques et médicales Elsevier</dc:rights>
</oai_dc:dc>