<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Variations metaboliques des communautes bacteriennes lors d'une pollution par petrole brut, avec ou sans traitement</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Cauchi, B</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>Bacteria</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Data processing</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Pollution effects</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Crude oil</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Marine pollution</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Physiology</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Metabolism</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Microbiology</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>Metabolic potentialities of bacterial communities in marine water after Crude Oil pollution (Arabian Light) and in marine water after pollution and treatment (enrichment: Inipol EAP 22) have been studied and compared. With data analysis: regressions, hierarchical ascending classification and multifactor correspondence analysis, the treatment gives rise to conservation and one increase of enzymatic pool (second day) of the bacterial sample as a combined metabolic homogeneity contrary to pollution impact. The direct assimilation of hydrocarbons looks more regular and slow without treatment.</dc:description>
  <dc:description>Les potentialités métaboliques des communautés bactériennes d'une eau de mer polluée par pétrole brut (Arabian Light) et d'une eau de mer polluée et traitée (apport d'une solution nutritive : Inipol EAP 22) ont été étudiées et comparées. De l'analyse des données : droites de régression, classification hiérarchique ascendante même l'augmentation du pool enzymatique (second jour) de l'échantillon bactérien ainsi qu'une homogénéité métabolique d'ensemble à l'inverse des effets de la pollution. L'assimilation des hydrocarbures par les bactéries semble être plus régulière et plus lente sans traitement.</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>Actes de colloques. Ifremer Brest [ACTES COLLOQ. IFREMER.]. 1986</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>1984-10</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Conference article</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/1984/acte-1023.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:language>fr</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/1023/</dc:relation>
</oai_dc:dc>