<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Etude d'une gestion optimale des pecheries de langoustines et de poissons demersaux en mer Celtique</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Laurec, Alain</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Charuau, Anatole</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Perodou, Jean-bernard</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Nedelec, Daniel</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Biseau, Alain</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Durand, Jean-louis</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Rivoalen, Jean-jacques</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Dupouy, Herve</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Le Louarn, G.</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Leroux, L.</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>monk</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>cuckoo ray</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>blue whiting</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>cod</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>hake</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>ling</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>common dab</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>data bases</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>fishing statistics</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>French fisheries</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>demersal fish</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Nephrops</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Celtic Sea</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>baudroies</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>raie fleurie</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>julienne</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>cardine</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>morue</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>merlu</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>merlan</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>base de données</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>rejets</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>statistiques de pêche</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>pêcheries françaises</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>poissons demersaux</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>langoustine</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Mer Celtique</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>The general study, scheduled from 1984 to 1986, aims at providing a judgement about the fisheries in the Celtic Sea. This area has been chosen because it is frequented by EEC vessels with, for the time being, a large majority of French vessels. Activities there are easier to monitor than anywhere else as coastal fisheries are little developed in the area. The final product will consist of a certain number of hypotheses about the planning strategies that could be implemented in the Celtic Sea. The main idea is, firstly, to conduct analytical studies, stock by stock, in order then, to synthesize them into a model integrating the interactions between fleets in relation to their target species. A bio-economical model, deriving from the latter, will enable the simulation of the consequences of the current planning procedures on the management of stocks and vessels.</dc:description>
  <dc:description>L'étude générale, programmée de 1984 à 1986, vise à fournir un avis sur les pêcheries de Mer Celtique. Cette zone a été choisie car elle est fréquentée par les flottilles de la CEE avec cependant, pour le moment, une dominante française quasi exclusive. Les activités qui s'y exercent peuvent être cernées plus facilement que partout ailleurs car les pêcheries côtières sont très peu développées. Le produit final consistera dans la présentation d'un certain nombre d'hypothèses sur les stratégies d'aménagement adaptables à la Mer Celtique. La voie choisie consiste, dans un premier temps, dans des études analytiques, stock par stock, puis dans leur synthèse dans un modèle intégrant les interactions entre flottilles en relation en particulier avec la recherche des espèces-cibles. Un modèle bio-économique, dérivé du précédent, permettra de simuler les conséquences des procédures habituelles d'aménagement sur la gestion des stocks et des flottilles.</dc:description>
  <dc:date>1985-10-02</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Report</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/1985/rapport-3671.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:language>fr</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/3671/</dc:relation>
</oai_dc:dc>