<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>The Western Adriatic shelf clinoform: energy-limited bottomset</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Cattaneo, Antonio</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Trincardi, Fabio</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Asioli, Alessandra</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Correggiari, Annamaria</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>Bottom currents</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Accommodation</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Regime model</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Bottomset</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Clinoform</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Adriatic</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>Clinoforms on modern shelves and slopes, as well as in ancient rock records, are widely recognized as a fundamental building element of continental margin growth. Regardless of their dominant lithology, clinoforms are composed of three geometric elements: topset, foreset and bottomset. Traditionally, much emphasis in the study of clinoforms was put on the geometry of the topset, viewed as the most energetic portion of a clinoform and studied to discern if aggradation was active rather than erosional truncation, and on the foreset, the area with the highest sediment accumulation rates. Here we focus on the factors forcing clinoforms to taper out and on the inferred mechanisms for bottomset creation. We base our analysis on muddy shelf clinoforms, a particular class of clinoforms that is typical of low-gradient settings and is characterized by a substantial component of shore-parallel sediment transport.

This paper is based on a large dataset of CHIRP-sonar profiles, bathymetric and isopach maps of the Late Holocene clinoform on the Adriatic shelf, where integrated stratigraphic studies from sediment cores allow a very high (in some cases century-scale) chronological resolution. Knowledge on the dominant oceanographic regime affecting sediment dispersal and, ultimately, clinoform development, has been recently refined during the EuroSTRATAFORM collaboration. Muddy clinoforms are markedly three-dimensional features that cannot be entirely understood solely on two-dimensional shore normal sections. We suggest that this class of clinoform is advection dominated and that an increase in the energy regime at the toe of the foreset may prevent sediment from reaching beyond the transition to the bottomset region.</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>Elsevier</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>2007-02</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Publication</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/2007/publication-2409.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:identifier>DOI:10.1016/j.csr.2006.11.013</dc:identifier>
  <dc:source>Continental Shelf Research (0278-4343) (Elsevier), 2007-02 , Vol. 27 , N. 3-4 , P. 506-525</dc:source>
  <dc:language>en</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/2409/</dc:relation>
  <dc:rights>2006 Elsevier Ltd All rights reserved</dc:rights>
</oai_dc:dc>