<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Recent progress in Penaeid shrimp culture</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Kittaka, Jiro</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>Histoire Ifremer</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>Hatahing and rearing of white shrimp (Penaeus setiferus), brown shrimp (Penaeus aztecus) and pink shrimp (Penaeus duorarum) were conducted at Panama City, Florida, U.S.A. , in a estuary site along the coast of the Gulf of Mexico. Using the large scale production method, 5.04 million white shrimp, 1.19 million brown shrimp and 1.63 million pink shrimp at advanced post-larval stage were produced per tank of 145 m  capacity. Survival rate from nauplius to postlarval shrimp Was 78.7 % for white shrimp, 25.2 % for brown shrimp, and 43.1 % for pink shrimp. White shrimp showed better growth rate during the early postlarval stage.  These shrimp were released into pens installed in the estuary. White shrimp showed better survival immediately after release compared to brown shrimp and pink shrimp even when released at smaller than 5 mg body weight. Survival rate for white shrimp at pen stage for about 20 days WaS 68.0 %.   It is concluded that non-grooved shrimp (white shrimp) has much better production efficiency compared to grooved shrimp (brown shrimp, pink shrimp, etc).</dc:description>
  <dc:description>L' éclosion et l'élevage de Penaeus setiferus, Penaeus aztecus et Penaeus duorarum ont été réalisés à Panama City (Floride, U.S.A.) dans un site d'estuaire, sur la côte du Mexique. Avec une méthode de production à grande échelle, il a été produit 5,04 millions de P. Setiferus, 1,19 millions de P. aztecus, et 1,63 millions de P. duorarum, à un stade postlarvaire avancé, par bac de 145 m3. Le taux de survie du nauplius à la post-larves est établi à 78,1 % pour P. Setiferus, 25,2 % pOUr P. aztecus, et 43,1 % pour P. duorarum. Le meilleur taux de croissance pendant l'élevage post-larvaire a été obtenu avec P. setiferue. Les crevettes ont été relâchées dans des enclos installés dans l'estuaire. Comparée aux autres espèces, P. Setiferus a fourni la meilleure survie après le lâcher, même lorsqu'il était réalisé à un poids inférieur à 5 mg. Le taux de survie de P. setiferus après 20 joUrs d'élevage en enclos s'est établi à 88,0 %. Il en est conclu que les crevettes non tigrées (P. setiferus) ont une efficacité de production bien meilleure que les crevettes tigrées (P. aztecus, P. duorarum, etc...).</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>Publ. CNEXO (France) (Actes Colloq.)(no. 7)</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>1977-05</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Conference article</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/1977/publication-6075.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:language>en</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/6075/</dc:relation>
</oai_dc:dc>