<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Particle selection in the oyster Crassostrea gigas (Thunberg) studied by pigment HPLC analysis under natural food conditions</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Pastoureaud, Annie</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Heral, Maurice</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Prou, Jean</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Razet, Daniel</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Russu, Patricia</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>Marennes Oleron Bay</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Biodeposits</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Selective feeding</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Crassostrea gigas</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Chloropigments</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Marennes Oléron</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Biodépots</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Tri particulaire</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Crassostrea gigas</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Chloropigments</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>Selective feeding in the adult oyster Crassostrea gigas was studied using natural particle assemblages in the estuarine environment of the Bassin de Marennes Oleron (France). Oysters were exposed to natural variations of suspended particulate matter by direct pumping of sea water from the bay during various tidal cycles. Experiments were conducted during the spring over both spring tides and neap tides, so as to obtain a maximum range of variation in seston characteristics, spring tide being characterized by very strong currents with high loads of resuspended materials (sediment, microphytobenthos and detritus). Particles were analysed for their chloropigment content by HPLC. The native pigments consisted exclusively of chlorophyll a and c, from both benthic and pelagic diatoms. Phaeophorbides were the main degradation products both in oyster faeces and in particles present in resuspended material, mainly composed of biodeposits. Comparisons between the composition of water-column particulate matter and pseudofaeces showed a negative selection against these detritus types by the oyster. This selective capacity was either not effective or was undetected at very high seston loads. Implications for the nutrition of Crassostrea gigas living in estuarine environments are discussed.</dc:description>
  <dc:description>La capacité de tri du matériel particulaire de l'huître Crassostrea gigas a été étudiée dans les conditions naturelles du Bassin de Marennes-Oléron (France). Les huîtres ont été exposées aux variations du matériel en suspension pendant différents cycles de marée. Les expériences se sont déroulées au printemps, en vives eaux et mortes-eaux afin de tester les conditions extrêmes de charges sestoniques rencontrées par les huîtres dans leur milieu d'élevage, les marées de vives-eaux étant caractérisées par des courants importants qui provoquent la remise en suspension de matériel benthique (sédiment, microphytobenthos et détritus). L'analyse du contenu en chloropigments de ces particules a été effectuée par HPLC. Les pigments non dégradés sont les chlorophylles a et c provenant des diatomées pélagiques et benthiques. Les phéophorbides sont les principaux produits de dégradation détectés dans les fécès d'huîtres et dans le matériel remis en suspension qui est probablement principalement constitué de biodépots. La comparaison entre la composition pigmentaire du matériel particulaire dans l'eau de mer et des pseudofécès a montré une selection négative vis-à-vis de ces détritus dans les conditions de faible charge sestonique. Cette capacité de selection était non effective ou indétectable aux fortes charges sestoniques (&gt; 100 mg.l-1). Les conséquences pour la nutrition de Crassostrea gigas dans son environnement sont discutées.</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>Elsevier</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>1995</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Publication</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/1995/publication-3085.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:source>Aquaculture (Elsevier), 1995 , Vol. 19 , N. 1 , P. 79-88</dc:source>
  <dc:language>en</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/3085/</dc:relation>
</oai_dc:dc>