<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>From biology and corrosion to biocorrosion</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Crolet, Jl</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>MARINE CORROSION</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>SULFATE-REDUCING BACTERIA</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>STEEL</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>STAINLESS STEEL</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>The treatment of certain cases of corrosion in living environments involves the consideration of two quite different disciplines, namely biology and corrosion. Either one or the other will be preponderant, according to the problem and the circumstances, and the two aspects are not necessarily permanently interdependent. Since the difficulties inherent in any multidisciplinary research are particularly pronounced for two such disparate fields, training and information exchange are of paramount importance. The need to harmonize terminology and concepts signifies, for the biologists, the use of a more chemically precise vocabulary and the abandonment of certain outdated theories, such as the notion of "cathodic depolarization", which are incompatible with modem electrochemical ideas. Until now, no specific mechanism of biological corrosion has yet been identified, the phenomenon being simply associated with particular local chemistries of living corrosive media. The most useful contribution of the biologists would be accurately to describe this chemistry, in terms that meet the requirements of the corrosion engineer. In particular, the precise quantification of bacterial metabolisms would be especially appreciated. While the generic term "biocorrosion" has become highly topical, it also incorporates past misunderstandings. The less ambitious expression "corrosion in living media", which conforms more closely to reality, would be certainly more reasonable.</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>Gauthier-Villars</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>1992</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Publication</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00101/21235/18852.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:source>Oceanologica Acta (0399-1784) (Gauthier-Villars), 1992 , Vol. 15 , N. 1 , P. 87-94</dc:source>
  <dc:language>en</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00101/21235/</dc:relation>
</oai_dc:dc>