<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Genetic polymorphism of glutamine synthetase and delta-9 desaturase in families of Pacific oyster Crassostrea gigas and susceptibility to summer mortality</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>David, Elise</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Boudry, Pierre</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Degremont, Lionel</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Tanguy, Amelie</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Quere, N</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Samain, Jean-francois</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Moraga, D</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>SSCP</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Mortality</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Glutamine synthetase</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Delta 9 desaturase</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Crassostrea gigas</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>Large-scale mortality events have been observed in Pacific oyster Crassostrea gigas on the west coast of France since the early 1980s, particularly during summer. In order to understand the causes of this mortality, two generations of oysters from single-pair matings were studied in three sites on the French Atlantic coast (Baie-des-Veys, Auray and Ronce-les-Bains). The present paper examines the role of two candidate genes in the susceptibility of oysters to summer mortality, and the selective pressure exerted by such mortality on their polymorphism. Glutamine synthetase (amino-acid metabolism) and delta-9 desaturase (lipid metabolism) genes were studied in the successive generations, using polymerase chain reaction single-strand conformation polymorphism (PCR-SSCP). Observed and expected genotypic frequencies were compared. Three different alleles were detected for the glutamine synthetase gene and two for delta-9 desaturase. Allele C of glutamine synthetase seemed to be counter-selected in some second generation families. Allele B of delta-9 desaturase gene was potentially counter-selected at Auray in the families showing higher mortality, and strong selection against 1313 homozygotes was observed. These observations led us to conclude that any selective effect of summer mortality on allele C of glutamine synthetase gene or allele B of delta-9 desaturase gene could be mediated either directly or via linkage to other loci involved in physiological pathways affecting susceptibility. (C) 2007 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>Elsevier</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>2007-10</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Publication</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/2007/publication-3040.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:identifier>DOI:10.1016/j.jembe.2007.05.016</dc:identifier>
  <dc:source>Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology (0022-0981) (Elsevier), 2007-10 , Vol. 349 , N. 2 , P. 272-283</dc:source>
  <dc:language>en</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/3040/</dc:relation>
  <dc:rights>2007 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved</dc:rights>
</oai_dc:dc>