<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Les Eaux Modales du gyre subpolaire de l'Atlantique Nord : origine, formation, variabilité</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>De Boisseson, Eric</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>ORCA025 G70</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>lagrangian analysis</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Argo</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>advection</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>atmospheric fluxes</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>North Atlantic current</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>subpolar gyre</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>North Atlantic</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Mode water</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>ORCA025 G70</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>analyse lagrangienne</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Argo</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>advection</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>flux atmosphériques</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Courant Nord Atlantique</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>gyre subpolaire</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Atlantique Nord</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Eau modale</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>The subpolar Mode Waters of the North Atlantic ocean play a key role in the general oceanic surface circulation. Their life cycle has only been described from an average of observations over several decades. This description avoids the real time scale of this life cycle and smooths its variaribility. It also does not adress the setting the Mode Water properties. This thesis work deals with these aspects by analysing both the ORCA025-G70 model fields and the observations.The lagrangian analysis of the ORCA025-G70 fields highlights the key role of the North Atlantic current in the life cycle of the Mode Waters. The Mode Waters are fed and carried by this current. They form during the winter mixed layer deepening due to the surface atmospheric fluxes. The Mode Waters are then rapidly (no more than 2 years) exported toward the Labrador Sea and the Nordic Seas. If the Mode Water formation is driven by the atmospheric fluxes, the Mode Water variability is driven by the advection via variable subpolar and subtropical contributions to the Mode Water feeding. We finally estimate from a mixed layer heat budget from both the Argo data and the ORCA025-G70 fields the relative contributions of the atmospheric fluxes, the advection and the turbulent mixing to the setting of the Mode Waters. We suggest that the Argo array should describe the variability of these processes over decadal time scales.</dc:description>
  <dc:description>Les Eaux Modales du gyre subpolaire de l'Atlantique Nord sont des éléments importants de la circulation de surface océanique dont le cycle de vie n'a été décrit qu'à partir de moyennes sur plusieurs décennies. Ces descriptions n'abordent pas les échelles de temps de ce cycle, lissent ses signaux de variabilité et s'attardent peu sur le conditionnement des Eaux Modales. Cette thèse aborde ces trois aspects grâce à une analyse complémentaire du modèle ORCA025-G70 et des observations. L'analyse lagrangienne dans ORCA025-G70 souligne l'importance du courant Nord Atlantique dans le cycle de vie des Eaux Modales. Les Eaux Modales sont alimentées puis transportées par ce courant et se forment dans la couche de mélange hivernale sous l'effet des flux atmosphériques. Elles sont exportées en 1 an ou 2 vers la Mer du Labrador et les Mers Nordiques. Si les flux atmosphériques dirigent la formation des Eaux Modales, la variabilité de leurs propriétés est dirigée par l'advection via des contributions subpolaires et subtropicales variables à l'alimentation des Eaux Modales. Le calcul du bilan de chaleur de couche de mélange à partir de données Argo et de ORCA025-G70 détermine enfin l'influence relative des flux atmosphériques, de l'advection et du mélange turbulent au conditionnement des Eaux Modales. Les résultats suggèrent que le réseau Argo devrait décrire la variabilité de ces processus sur des fenêtres de 10 ans.</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>Université de Bretagne Occidentale</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>2010-01-14</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Thesis</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/2010/these-7469.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:language>fr</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/7469/</dc:relation>
</oai_dc:dc>