<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Les associations bacteries-matiere particulaire en milieu pelagique cotier: Exemples de variations spatiales et temporelles</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Jacq, Estelle</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Prieur, D</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>ANE, France, Brittany</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Stratification</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Water masses</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Seasonal variations</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Bacteria</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Phytoplankton</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Epipsammon</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Microorganisms</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Suspended particulate matter</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>Studies concerning the respective role of free-living and particle-bound bacteria in pelagic ecosystems, sometimes gave opposite results. The comparative distribution of these bacterial patterns was studied in two sites of Brittany. In the Bay of Brest, a shallow and semi-enclosed area, the bacterial communities were dominated by the free-living forms, except during the phytoplankton bloom, which was accompanied by a clear increase of the particle-bound forms. Off the west coasts of Brittany, the Ushant front separates stratified water masses from mixed water masses. The distribution of particle-bound bacteria fluctuated according to the structure of the water masses and in mixed waters, was related to particulate matter from different origins. Results indicate that a previous knowledge of the distribution of bacterial patterns was necessary before the study of the role of the different components of the bacterial communities.</dc:description>
  <dc:description>La signification respective des bactéries libres et des bactéries fixées aux particules, en milieu pélagique, a fait l'objet d'observations parfois contradictoires. En préambule à un travail sur ce sujet, la distribution comparée de ces types bactériens a été étudiée en deux sites particuliers de Bretagne. En rade de Brest, milieu semi fermé, peu profond, les peuplements bactériens sont dominés par les formes libres, exception faite de la poussée printanière de phytoplancton qui est accompagnée d'une nette augmentation des formes fixées aux particules. En mer d'iroise, au niveau du système frontal d'Ouessant, cohabitent des masses d'eaux de structure thermique différentes : statifiée et mélangée. La distribution des bactéries fixées aux particules varie selon la masse d'eau considérée et en zone homogène correspond à du matériel particulate d'origines différentes. Les résultats indiquent la nécessité d'une connaissance préalable de la distribution des divers types bactériens avant d'aborder l'étude du rôle des différents composants du peuplement bactérien.</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>Actes de colloques. Ifremer Brest [ACTES COLLOQ. IFREMER.]. 1986</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>1984-10</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Conference article</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/1984/acte-965.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:language>fr</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/965/</dc:relation>
</oai_dc:dc>