<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Les pêcheries françaises du chalutage à bar : analyse de séries temporelles 1999-2007</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Morizur, Yvon</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Meunier, M</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Huet, Jerome</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Martin, S</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>fishing mortality</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>recruitment</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>abundance index</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>fishing effort</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>trawling</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>seabass</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Dicentrarchus labrax</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>mortalité par pêche</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>recrutement</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>indice d'abondance</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>effort de pêche</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>chalutage</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>bar commun</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Dicentrarchus labrax</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>A displacement of the fishing effort of the French pelagic trawlers from anchovy to the seabass fisheries is observed. A such situation on a non-quota managed species requires to analyse carefully the evolution in the status of seabass stocks. The evolution of fishing effort, the production and the landings per unit of effort were studied from 2000 to 2007 for the bottom trawling and for the pair pelagic trawling in the ICES sub-areas VIII and VII. The fishing effort was assessed by using a threshold on the landings by month in order to select the most effective fishing effort as representing 75 % of the effort concerned with seabass landings. Length compositions and age-length keys were used to calculate the cpue-at-age series. A total mortality value was assessed from the annual abundance index of each year class.
An increase of the fishing effort of pelagic trawling was detected in the English Channel area since 2005. Concomitantly, good recruitments (1999, 2000 and 2001 year classes) were observed in that area which could have stimulated the displacement of effort from anchovy towards seabass. These good year classes have also limited the negative impact of the fishing effort on the durability of the exploitation. The abundance in the English Channel in 2007 appears similar to the situation in 2003. A total mortality coefficient was assessed equal to 0.438 for combined areas VII &amp;VIII. This mortality estimate results from all the fishing components on the [7-11] years old fish and it includes also the impact of the recreational fisheries.
A relationship between total length and the circumference of the body was established for seabass of the English Channel - Celtic Sea areas. Such model is useful to determine the mesh to be used for adequacy with the minimum landing size. For instance, to catch only fish greater than 42 cm long, a stretched mesh size of 114 mm needs to be used; and the catch of animals of at least 8 years could be achieved with a 140 mm stretched mesh size.
The analysis which provides useful information on the evolution of the status of stocks requires to be updated as soon as possible.</dc:description>
  <dc:description>Au cours des dernières années, un report d'effort du chalutage pélagique a été observé de l'anchois vers le bar. Une telle évolution sur une espèce non soumise à quota annuel exige une analyse de la situation des stocks de bars. L'effort de pêche, la production ainsi que les rendements de pêche ont été analysés de 2000 à 2007 aussi bien pour le chalutage pélagique que pour le chalutage de fond. Ces analyses ont été faites sur les zones de pêche CIEM VII et VIII. Des indices d'abondance par âge ont pu être établis.
L'augmentation d'effort de pêche du chalutage pélagique a démarré en 2005 en Manche. Sur cette zone, de bons recrutements ont été observés avec les classes d'ages 1999, 2000 et 2001 qui pourraient avoir incité le report d'effort en générant de bons rendements. Ces bonnes classes ont aussi limité les effets négatifs d'une augmentation de la pression de pêche, si bien que les indices d'abondance observés en 2007 étaient au même niveau que ceux de 2003. Un coefficient instantané et moyen de mortalité totale a été établi à 0.438 pour l'ensemble des zones VII et VIII sur la tranche d'âge adulte des 7-11 ans. Ce coefficient prend en compte l'ensemble des impacts de la pêche sur la population adulte. Une analyse biométrique des poissons indique aussi qu'un maillage étiré de 114 mm permettrait d'être associé à une taille minimale de 42 cm et que, pour ne retenir que des animaux de 8 ans et plus, il faudrait un maillage de 140 mm. L'étude des indices d'abondance aux âges permet d'assurer une veille sur l'état des stocks concernés par ces métiers.</dc:description>
  <dc:date>2009-12</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Report</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/2009/rapport-7303.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:language>fr</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/7303/</dc:relation>
</oai_dc:dc>