<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Essai de caractérisation sous pression de panneaux en composites pour structures marines</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Reichard, R</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>Test equipment</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Loads (forces)</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Pressure effects</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Pressure</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Materials testing</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Ship technology</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Composite materials</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Panneau composite</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Pression répartie</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Choc</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Sandwich</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Essais</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>Traditional testing of FRP sandwich panels using uniaxial loading provides useful data for structural designers, but these tests do not work well for multiaxially reinforced laminates or for sandwich laminates. Sandwich laminates are generally used to increase the flexural properties of a panel. Flexural testing of sandwich beams does not address panel membrane effects, which can be significant. As a result, a number of different methods have been developed for testing panels. Experiments with multiaxial FRP sandwich panels have been conducted to evaluate the behavior of panel laminates with various fiber orientations and core materials under both static pressure loading and hydrodynamic shock loading. The test apparatus and methods are described, and the results of several experiments are summarized in this paper.</dc:description>
  <dc:description>Les essais traditionnels sur panneaux sandwich FRP utilisant une charge uniaxiale fournissent des données intéressantes pour les concepteurs de structure, mais ces essais ne conviennent pas bien pour les stratifiés renforcés multiaxiaux ou sandwichs. Les stratifiés sandwichs sont en général utilisés pour accroître les propriétés en flexion d'un panneau. Les essais en flexion des poutres sandwichs ne prennent pas en compte les effets de membrane de panneau qui peuvent être importants. Un certain nombre de différentes méthodes ont donc été développées pour tester les panneaux. Des expériences avec des sandwichs FRP multiaxiaux ont été réalisées pour évaluer le comportement des panneaux stratifiés avec diverses orientations de fibres et matériaux d'âme, à la fois sous charge statique et sous choc hydrodynamique. L'appareillage et les méthodes sont décrits, et les résultats de plusieurs expériences sont résumés.</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>Actes de colloques. Ifremer. Brest [ACTES COLLOQ. IFREMER.]. 1992</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>1992-12</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Conference article</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/1992/acte-1086.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:language>fr</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/1086/</dc:relation>
</oai_dc:dc>