<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Scales characterising a high density thin layer of Dinophysis acuta Ehrenberg and its transport within a coastal jet</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Farrell, Hazel</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Gentien, Patrick</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Fernand, Liam</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Lunven, Michel</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Reguera, Beatriz</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Gonzalez-gil, Sonsoles</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Raine, Robin</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>Coastal jets</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Dinophysis</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Ireland</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Transport</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>An investigation into the distribution of Dinophysis spp. in coastal waters off the south coast of Ireland was carried out in July 2007. Dinophysis acuta was present as a sub surface layer containing up to 55,000 cells L-1. The population had a high percentage of viable cells (mean: 89%; median: 94%; n = 24)
with a high specific division rate (~0.55 d-1). The layer, of approximately 5 m thickness, did not coincide with the fluorescence maximum and was present as a patch of horizontal dimension less than 10 km x 7 km. Both conventional and towed undulating CTD used in conjunction with high vertical resolution sampling methods showed the patch of Dinophysis to move with a similar speed and direction as the coastal flow, which ran parallel to the coast in the form of a coastal jet with speed of the order of 6.5–7 km day-1. The implications of the alongshore transport of populations of harmful species in coastal jets for monitoring programmes and predictive models are discussed.</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>Elsevier Science Bv</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>2012-03</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Publication</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00064/17538/17420.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:identifier>DOI:10.1016/j.hal.2011.11.003</dc:identifier>
  <dc:source>Harmful Algae (1568-9883) (Elsevier Science Bv), 2012-03 , Vol. 15 , P. 36-46</dc:source>
  <dc:language>en</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00064/17538/</dc:relation>
  <dc:rights>2011 Elsevier B.V.</dc:rights>
</oai_dc:dc>