<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>L'amélioration des performances de l'huître plate européenne Ostrea edulis par la sélection génétique</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Bedier, Edouard</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Baud, Jean-pierre</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Cochennec, Nathalie</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Cornette, Florence</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Gerard, Andre</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Goyard, Emmanuel</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Joly, Jean-pierre</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Kopp, Joel</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Langlade, Aime</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Le Coguic, Yvette</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Mazurie, Joseph</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Nourry, Max</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>Bonamia ostrea</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Huître plate</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Sélection Génétique</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Ostrea edulis</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>The European flat oyster Ostrea edulis has been considered as the traditional French oyster for a very long time and has now nearly disappeared from our farms, as a consequence of the two successive epizootic of the Marteilia refringens parasite and Bonamia ostreae. The actual quasi monoculture of Crassostrea gigas has made necessary the search for a diversification in oyster culture, including the search for a new start of the indigenous flat oyster culture. The Ifremer has been conducting parallel works since 1985 in order to better understand the biology of the parasite as well as to try and select different lines of flat oyster resistant to Bonamia ostreae.</dc:description>
  <dc:description>Longtemps considérée comme l'huître traditionnelle des côtes françaises, l'huître plate européenne Ostrea edulis a quasiment disparu des parcs français, suite aux épizooties successives des parasites Marteilia refringens, puis Bonamia ostreae. La quasi monoculture actuelle de Crassostrea gigas rend nécessaire la recherche d'une diversification de l'activité ostréicole, dont celle des moyens de relance de la culture de l'huître plate indigène. Ifremer mène parallèlement depuis 1985 des travaux pour mieux connaître la biologie du parasite et pour vérifier la possibilité de sélectionner des lignées d'huîtres plates résistantes à Bonamia ostreae.</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>Actes Journées Conchylicoles, Ifremer Nantes, 3-4 avril 2001</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>2001-04-04</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Conference article</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/2001/acte-3274.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:language>fr</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/3274/</dc:relation>
</oai_dc:dc>