<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Crustaces profonds captures aux casiers aux Antilles françaises - 1996</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Paulmier, Gerard</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>Crab</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Prawn</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Shrimp</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Depth</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Crustaceas</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Inventory</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>French Antillean</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Crabe</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Langoustine</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Crevette</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Profond</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Crustace</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Inventaire</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Antilles françaises</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>For several years the fishermen of the West Indies have directed their activities towards new fishing grounds, notably the bathyales zones adjacent to island plateaux up to approximately 1000 metres in depth. Explorations carried out since 1989 have shown that diverse crustacean populations could be exploited. However, populations and exploitable stocks are not well known. The use of crustaceans traps as a fishing technique permits the capture of shellfish, shrimps and prawns of which at least six species could have commercial interest. The main objective of this work is do draw up an inventory of the principal commercial species as well as the accompanying species belonging to the subordres Decapoda macrura, anomura, brachyura and to the orders Isopoda and Amphipoda. It is intended for fishermen and other socio-professionals of the fishing industry. It should enable them to identify and name these previously unexploited varieties of Crustacea to facilitate their sale in local markets.</dc:description>
  <dc:description>Depuis quelques années, des pêcheurs antillais orientent leurs activités vers de nouveaux secteurs de pêche, notamment les zones bathyales adjacentes aux plateaux insulaires, jusque vers 1000 mètres de profondeur. Des campagnes exploratoires menées depuis 1989, ont montré que diverses populations carcinologiques pouvaient faire l'objet d'une exploitation. Toutefois, populations et stocks exploitables ne sont pas bien connus. L'emploi du casier comme technique de pêche, permet la capture de crustacés, crevettes et langoustines, dont au moins 6 espèces peuvent avoir un intérêt commercial. Ce travail nomenclatural a pour premier objectif de dresser l'inventaire des principales espèces commerciales ainsi que des espèces accompagnatrices appartenant aux infra-ordres des Décapodes macroures, anomoures, brachyoures, et aux ordres des Isopodes et des Amphipodes. Il est destiné aux pêcheurs et aux autres personnes des catégories socio-professionnelles de la filière pêche. Il devrait leur permettre d'identifier et de nommer ces produits nouveaux pour faciliter leur vente sur les marchés locaux.</dc:description>
  <dc:date>1996-12</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Report</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/1996/rapport-1543.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:language>fr</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/1543/</dc:relation>
</oai_dc:dc>