<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Complete genome sequence of acute viral necrosis virus associated with massive mortality outbreaks in the Chinese scallop, Chlamys farreri</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Ren, Weicheng</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Chen, Haixia</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Renault, Tristan</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Cai, Yuyong</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Bai, Changming</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Wang, Chongming</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Huang, Jie</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>Acute viral necrosis virus (AVNV)</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Herpesvirus</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>OsHV-1</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Genome</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>Acute viral necrosis virus (AVNV) is the causative agent of a serious disease resulting in high mortality in cultured Chinese scallops, Chlamys farreri. We have sequenced and analyzed the complete genome of AVNV. The AVNV genome is a linear, double-stranded DNA molecule of 210,993 bp with a nucleotide composition of 38.5% G + C. A total of 123 open reading frames were predicted to encode functional proteins, ranging from 41 to 1,878 amino acid residues. The DNA sequence of AVNV is 97% identical to that of ostreid herpesvirus 1 (OsHV-1), and the amino acid sequences of the encoded proteins of these two viruses are 94-100% identical. The genomic organization of AVNV is similar to that of OsHV-1, and consists of two unique regions (170.4 kb and 3.4 kb, respectively), each flanked by two inverted repeats (7.6 kb and 10.2 kb, respectively), with a third unique region (1.5 kb) situated between the two internal repeats. Our results indicate that AVNV is a variant of OsHV-1. The AVNV genome sequence provides information useful for understanding the evolution and divergence of OsHV-1 in marine molluscs.</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>Biomed Central Ltd</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>2013-04</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Publication</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00135/24620/22650.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:identifier>DOI:10.1186/1743-422X-10-110</dc:identifier>
  <dc:source>Virology Journal (1743-422X) (Biomed Central Ltd), 2013-04 , Vol. 10 , P. -</dc:source>
  <dc:language>en</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00135/24620/</dc:relation>
  <dc:rights>2013 Ren et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</dc:rights>
</oai_dc:dc>