<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Effect of past nutritional history and fasting on feed intake and growth in rainbow trout Oncorhynchus mykiss</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Boujard, Thierry</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Burel, Christine</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Medale, Francoise</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Haylor, Graham</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Moisan, Annick</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>Feed efficiency</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Appetite</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Past nutritional history</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Compensatory growth</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Aquaculture</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>Groups of juvenile rainbow trout were fed to satiation for 10 days after 1, 11 and 21 days of feed deprivation. These fish (initial body weight =20 +/- 2 g) were previously fed at different feeding levels (0.5 or 1.5% initial body weight, to satiation) with a high (20.4 kJ . g(-1)) or a low (16.2 kJ.g(-1)) digestible energy diet content for 34 days. It is shown that past nutritional history affected growth performance: duration of feed deprivation has a major effect on intake and feed conversion efficiency; previous feeding level has an effect on intake; dietary energy content affected feed conversion efficiency. In addition, an attempt was made to identify some of the metabolic parameters that could be involved in the increase in growth performance during the 10-day feeding period (whole body and muscle protein and lipid, plasma glucose, free fatty acids and triglycerids). Feed intake after fasting does not appear to be driven by body composition but feed conversion efficiency was correlated with the plasma glucose and free fatty acids. (C) 2000 Ifremer/Cnrs/Inra/Ird/Cemagref/Editions scientifiques et medicales Elsevier SAS.</dc:description>
  <dc:description>Des groupes de truites arc-en-ciel juvéniles ont été nourris à satiété durant dix jours après 1, 11 ou 21 jours de jeûne. Au préalable, ces poissons (poids INITIAL = 20 ± 2 g) étaient alimentés à différents taux de rationnement (0,5 ou 1,5 % du poids initial ou à satiété) avec un aliment à haute (20,4 kJ·g¿1) ou basse (16,2 kJ·g¿1) teneur en énergie digestible durant 34 jours. Cette étude montre que le passé nutritionnel affecte la performance de croissance des truites arc-en-ciel : le niveau d'ingestion volontaire est significativement différent selon la durée du jeûne et le taux de rationnement passé, tandis que l'efficacité alimentaire est significativement influencée par la durée du jeûne et le niveau d'énergie de l'aliment. On a aussi essayé d'identifier l'existence d'un lien entre la composition corporelle et musculaire, la concentration du plasma en glucose, acides gras libres et triglycérides en fin de période de jeune et les caractéristiques de la croissance au cours de la période de réalimentation. Aucun lien significatif entre la composition corporelle et le niveau d'ingestion volontaire n'a pu être mis en évidence. En revanche, l'efficacité alimentaire est corrélée avec la concentration en glucose et en acides gras libres du plasma.</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>Elsevier</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>2000-05</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Publication</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/2000/publication-1399.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:identifier>DOI:10.1016/S0990-7440(00)00149-2</dc:identifier>
  <dc:source>Aquatic Living Resources (0990-7440) (Elsevier), 2000-05 , Vol. 13 , N. 3 , P. 129-137</dc:source>
  <dc:language>en</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/1399/</dc:relation>
  <dc:rights>2000 Ifremer/Cnrs/Inra/Ird/Cemagref/Éditions scientifiques et médicales Elsevier SAS</dc:rights>
</oai_dc:dc>