<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Determination du profil des flores bacteriennes des zones littorales. Application a l'evaluation de l'impact des rejets</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Bunetel, L</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Segui, A</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Guerin, J</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Lerman, I</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Cormier, M</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>Bacteria</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Coastal waters</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Microbiological culture</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Sewage disposal</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Microbial contamination</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Bacterial counters</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Bacteria collecting devices</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>The principle of this method is to evaluate, by counts exercised upon selective media, the relative importance of the different bacteria families in the flora of the coastal waters. It is important to separate the contaminant species and the commensal species in the marine environment. Ten culture media distributed into four categories (selective, non selective, saline and non saline) were examined by numeration. Counts were transferred on a diagram allowing to plot down a profile of bacterial flora of water sampled from a given geographical area. The profiles are arranged by a classification method. The sampling points with similar or adjoining profiles were assembled and marked on the chart. In this way, the authors obtained areas representing the impact zone of disposal of disturbed zones of flora that have remained stable during this study.</dc:description>
  <dc:description>Le principe de la méthode est d'évaluer, grâce à des numérations sur milieux sélectifs, l'importance relative des différentes familles bactériennes dans la flore des eaux de mer littorales. Il est important de séparer milieux de cultures, répartis en quatre classes : milieux sélectifs, non sélectifs, salés, non salés. Les numérations sont reportées sur un diagramme permettant d'établir un profil de la flore bactérienne de l'eau prélevée en un point géographiquement donné. Les profils sont groupés par une méthode de classification. Les points de prélèvements dont les profils sont semblables ou voisins sont rassemblés et repérés sur la carte. Nous obtenons pendant la durée de l'étude.</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>Actes de colloques. Ifremer Brest [ACTES COLLOQ. IFREMER.]. 1986</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>1984-10</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Conference article</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/1984/acte-1004.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:language>fr</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/1004/</dc:relation>
</oai_dc:dc>