<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Generation of a residual current by interaction between the coastal boundary-layer and the ekman layer in a tidal motion</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Aelbrecht, D</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Dhieres, Gc</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Zhang, Xz</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>TIDAL CURRENTS</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>BOUNDARY LAYER</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>EKMAN LAYER</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>RESIDUAL CURRENT</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>Some experiments have been made with the large rotating tank at the Institut de Mecanique de Grenoble to reproduce a sinusoidal flow along a vertical wall, over a flat bottom, with or without slope, in a homogeneous fluid. The objective of these experiments was to simulate a tidal motion, restricted to its main harmonic component M2, parallel to a vertical coast; and to demonstrate a particular mode of generation of residual circulation near the coast as a result of the interaction between friction, background rotation of the system (Ekman pumping) and oscillatory motion (Stokes effects). Moreover, the stabilizing (or otherwise) effects of the Earth's rotation on this shear flow may modify the rectification process. The configuration is in a good agreement with the general topographic and hydrographic situation along the French coast  of  the  Pas-de-Calais  near Boulogne-sur-Mer. In the Northern hemisphere, the bottom current is diverted to the left of the main current due to. the balance between the Coriolis force and the pressure gradient. This imposes a dissymetric behaviour of the flow between flux and ebb, as well as the generation of an alternative component perpendicular to the coastline, together with lateral transport (vertical close to the coasts) of horizontal momentum which modifies the coastal boundary layer. A rectified (residual) current is observed with the coast to its right. Experiments were systematically made on a flat bottom moving in the rotating tank by varying the main parameters of the flow;  and we measured the velocity field with ultrasonic velocimetric probes and photographs of surface floats. The results (amplitude and width of the rectified current) show a good correlation with the few observations at sea and with the scaling analysis we provide.</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>Gauthier-Villars</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>1993</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Publication</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00100/21139/18759.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:source>Oceanologica Acta (0399-1784) (Gauthier-Villars), 1993 , Vol. 16 , N. 5-6 , P. 479-487</dc:source>
  <dc:language>en</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00100/21139/</dc:relation>
</oai_dc:dc>