<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Influence of dry diets on reproductive performance and egg lipid composition during the first spawning season of captive pollack</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Omnes, Marie-helene</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Recek, Sophie</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Barone, Herve</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Le Delliou, Herve</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Schmitz, Audrey</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Mutelet, Alexis</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Suquet, Marc</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Robin, Jean H.</dc:creator>
  <dc:description>Four‐year‐old pollack Pollachius pollachius L., previously fed on dry pellets since their juvenile stage, were divided into three experimental groups two months prior their first spawning season. They were fed a commercial broodstock pellet enriched with 6% added oils, either: (1) capelin oil (control), (2) capelin oil plus arachidonic acid, or (3) DHA rich tuna oil. Spawning performance was determined in each group and egg lipids were analysed. During the vitellogenic period, the estradiol levels in plasma increased with oocyte enlargement, indicating that captivity and pelleted feed did not affect reproductive capacity. Females from each group spawned spontaneously between February and May. Egg production per kg of female was highest in the control group. Fertilization rate was highest (39%) in the group fed on diet enhanced in DHA. Lipid content in eggs reached 16% of dry mass, containing mainly phospholipids (75%). Egg fatty acid profiles showed few differences between dietary treatments. There was no significant difference in the concentration of Docosahexaenoic acid (22:6n − 3) between groups. Arachidonic acid (20:4n − 6) was lower in neutral and polar lipids of eggs from the control group than in the other groups. Tuna oil diet induced the highest DHA/EPA ratio in eggs and seemed to provide sufficient arachidonic acid for pollack broodstock. Egg fatty acid profiles are compared with 6 year‐old pollack broodstock fed on fish, and with other cultured and wild fish species.</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>"Nature and Culture" Comparative Biology and Interactions of Wild and Farmed Fish. Annual International Conference. Imperial College, London, 19-23 July 2004</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>2004</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Poster</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00002/11322/7859.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:language>en</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00002/11322/</dc:relation>
  <dc:rights>Ifremer</dc:rights>
</oai_dc:dc>