<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>La baie de Seine : hydrologie, nutriments, chlorophille (1978-1994)</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Aminot, Alain</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Guillaud, Jean-francois</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Kerouel, Roger</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>Chlorophyll</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Nutrients</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Hydrology</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Bay of Seine</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Chlorophylle</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Nutriments</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Hydrologie</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Baie de Seine</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>The data of hydrology, nutrients and chlorophyll obtained in the Bay of Seine over the period 1978-1994, from 14 océanographie cruises, are synthetised and illustrated by an atlas. The Bay is a typical example of a coastal area influenced by a large river. In winter, the nutrient input is drained off into the eastern Channel. In spring, nutrients are consumed intensively. Silicate is the first that drops to limiting levels. The spring bloom generally begins in the centre-east of the Bay. Chlorophyll a can reach up to 40-70 µg/l during the year, values typical of eutrophic coastal areas. Despite the regular increase of nitrogen inputs, the biomass (as chlorophyll) has not significantly changed over a fifteen year period.</dc:description>
  <dc:description>Les données d'hydrologie, de nutriments et de chlorophylle acquises en baie de Seine de 1978 à 1994, grâce à 14 campagnes océanographiques, sont synthétisées et complétées par une illustration sous forme d'atlas. Ce site constitue un exemple type de zone côtière soumise à l'influence d'un grand fleuve. En hiver, l'apport fluvial de nutriments s'évacue en Manche est. Au printemps, ceux-ci sont intensément consommés, le silicate chutant le premier à des niveaux limitants. La poussée printanière débute souvent dans le Centre-Est de la baie. La chlorophylle a (jusqu'à 40 à 70 µg/l dans l'année) est typique d'une zone côtière eutrophe. Malgré l'accroissement régulier des apports d'azote, la biomasse chlorophyllienne évolue peu sur une quinzaine d'années.</dc:description>
  <dc:date>1997</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Book</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/1997/rapport-1428.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:language>fr</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/1428/</dc:relation>
</oai_dc:dc>