<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Abondance et distribution des larves d'araignée (Maia squinado Herbst) en Manche en 1983</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Martin, Jocelyne</dc:creator>
  <dc:description>Zooplancton was sampled during 1983 on the french coast of English Channel, near Paluel (eastern Channel),near Flamanville (west coast of Cotentin) and in the bay of Saint-Malo. This paper. presents the results obtained about the larvae of the spinous spider crab (Maia squinado, Herbst).Seasonal cycles of abundance of zoeal ang megalopa stages are shown for all the stations studied in 1983. The distribution of zoeal stages is given for the two cruises which took place as zoea were most abundant. Previous results from Paluel and Flamanville are discussed to relate earlier hatchings with higher sea temperatures at the beginning of summer in 1983. NOT CONTROLLED OCR</dc:description>
  <dc:description>Des prélèvements de zooplancton ont été effectués en 1983 en Manche, à Paluel (Manche est), à Flamanville (côte ouest du Cotentin) et dans un secteur plus élargi du golfe normano-breton. Cette note présente les résultats obtenus pour les larves d'araignée (Maia sguinado Herbst). Les variations saisonnières d'abondance des zoés et des mégalopes sont représentées pour l'ensemble des points étudiés en 1983. Une carte de répartition géographique est donnée pour chacune des deux campagnes effectuées lors des effectifs maximums. Les résultats antérieurs obtenus à Paluel et Flamanville sont repris afin de mettre en relation la précocité des éclosions de 1983 et les températures plus élevées au début de l'été. OCR NON CONTRÔLE</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>Conseil International pour l'Exploration de la Mer (CIEM). C.M. 1985/K : 24</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>1985</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Conference article</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/1985/acte-3916.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:language>fr</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/3916/</dc:relation>
</oai_dc:dc>