<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Contrôle de la ploidie par imagerie numérique dans des expériences d'induction de la triploidie chez les mollusques bivalves</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Gerard, Andre</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Peignon, Jean-marie</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Chagot, Dominique</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>Image cytometry</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Caryology</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Triploidy</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Bivalve</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Imagerie numérique</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Caryologie</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Triploïdie</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Bivalve</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>Individual determination of ploidy level in experimentally induced triploid bivalve molluscs using image cytometry. The sexual maturation in bivalve molluscs causes decreased growth and sometimes increased mortalities. These drawbacks can be avoided by genetic sterilization (triploidy). Triploïdy induction require a egg treatment and a ploidy control at each generation. The ploidy level is usually determined by counting the chromosomes, a technique which is relatively easy for the trochophora stage and for juveniles measuring from 5 mm to 3 cm only.  ln order to be able to follow up the evolution of the ploidy rate during any stage of animallife, we have developed an estimation method based on image cytometry. Individual DNA content is determined by integrated optical density of Feulgen-stained nuclei. The technique can be used for routine examination. The reaction is stoechiometric and the reading is quantitative. If compared to chromosome counting, image cytometry is more reliable. Moreover, it is simpler than flow cytometry.</dc:description>
  <dc:description>La maturation sexuelle chez les mollusques bivalves entraîne une diminution de la croissance somatique et parfois une augmentation de la mortalité. Ces inconvénients peuvent être éliminés par stérilisation génétique (triploïdisation). L'induction de la triploïdie nécessite un traitement des oeufs et un contrôle de la ploïdie à chaque génération. Le niveau de ploïdie est habituellement déterminé par comptage des chromosomes, mais cette technique n'est vraiment facile à mettre en oeuvre que pour le stade trocophore et les juvéniles mesurant de 5 mm à 3 cm seulement. Pour être capable de suivre l'évolution du taux de triploïdie pendant toute la vie de l'animal, nous avons développé une méthode basée sur l'analyse de l'image du noyau. Le contenu individuel en ADN est déterminé par mesure de la densité optique intégrée du noyau coloré par la réaction de Feulgen. Cette technique peut être utilisée en routine. La réaction est stoechiométrique et la lecture quantitative. Comparée au comptage des chromosomes, l'analyse d'image est plus fiable et elle est aussi plus simple que la cytométrie en flux.</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>Counc. Meet. of the Int. Counc. for the Exploration of the Sea, (La Rochelle (France)), (26 Sep-4 Oct 1991)</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>1991-09-26</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Conference article</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/1991/acte-3202.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:language>fr</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/3202/</dc:relation>
</oai_dc:dc>