<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Aquaculture et prospective : un passé simple et ses futurs antérieurs</dc:title>
  <dc:title>Aquaculture and prospective : a simple past and its future past</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Lacroix, Denis</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>Aquaculture</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>prospective</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>durabilité</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Macrobrachium rosenbergii</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Aquaculture</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>foresight analysis</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>sustainability</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Macrobrachium rosenbergii</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>Aquaculture is one of the main supply of protein in feed for mankind, notably in Asia. It increases and had exceeded the level of production of world fisheries, which is decreasing. According to sites and rearing methods, aquaculture contributes to add value but also in some cases to impact negatively the aquatic ecosystems. In the coastal area, a rich and productive zone, but also a place of conflicts, this activity presents a high potential for development if it takes into account the rules of sustainability. The conditions of this sustainability may be cleared with appropriate methods of foresight analysis applied for each development project. The analysis of the professional experience of D. Lacroix for 33 years in aquaculture is structured in three steps. Firstly, the work is to check the scientific value of the research conducted under his responsibility in various contexts and for different responsibilities. This study refers to the requirements of a PhD. In the second part of the work, the results of few major projects (French West Indies, French Guyana….) are analysed with the support of the theory of translation (Callon et al) which allows to build a network of actors and to project it into the context. This way of study includes a special attention to the aspects of time planning, legitimacy and acceptability. Finally, the author examines how this knowledge gained from experience could help building a method for foresight analysis aiming at a shorter planning, a better timing and less means for future projects. To achieve this goal the author integrates the vision of the economist R. Passet which structures any project in an ecosystemic framework, including criteria of sustainability. The mix of these two approaches (Callon &amp; Passet) entails in a new tool for foresight analysis, called Aster, which originality is to offer the possibility to test various scenarios and related consequences to help decision -makers. This new method of foresight analysis, is then tested on the well known case study of the development of prawn Macrobrachium rosenbergii in French Guyana. The test shows to be successful as it delivers precise and arguable recommendations about research and development for all stakeholders.</dc:description>
  <dc:description>L'aquaculture est l'une des composantes principales de l'apport en protéines dans le monde, surtout en Asie. Elle croît, alors que la pêche, qu'elle a dépassée en tonnage comme en valeur, décline. Selon les écosystèmes et les méthodes employées, elle peut contribuer à valoriser, mais aussi à dégrader les milieux aquatiques. Dans la zone côtière, espace riche et productif au plan biologique mais convoité, l'aquaculture conserve un potentiel de développement si sa mise en œuvre intègre les principes de la durabilité. Celle-ci peut être éclairée par la prospective avec des méthodes d'analyse adaptées à chaque projet. L'analyse de l'expérience de 33 ans en aquaculture de D. Lacroix est faite en trois temps. D'abord, il s'agit de vérifier la qualité de ses travaux de recherche scientifique menés dans des contextes et avec des responsabilités variés en suivant la grille d'analyse de référence d'un doctorat. Ensuite, l'analyse consiste à prendre un recul critique sur les bilans de réalisations majeures (Antilles, Guyane…) en mobilisant l'approche de M. Callon dont la théorie de la traduction permet de construire le réseau des acteurs et de le projeter dans la problématique. Cette grille d'analyse est complétée par l'étude des aspects de temporalité, légitimité et d'acceptabilité pour chaque réalisation. Ce travail sur diverses situations d'intervention permet de préparer une réflexion sur la proposition méthodologique qui suit et son adaptation à des conditions variables. Enfin, les connaissances acquises sont synthétisées afin de construire une méthode de prospective qui permettrait de gagner en temps, en efficacité et en moyens sur des projets à venir. Pour cela, l'analyse s'appuie sur la vision de R. Passet, qui structure les éléments de tout projet dans la hiérarchie des composantes de la durabilité. Le système dynamique qui en résulte peut être alors croisé avec divers scénarios afin d'en simuler les conséquences et donc d‟éclairer les choix. Cette méthode, dite Aster, est testée sur le cas « modèle » et bien documenté de l'élevage de la crevette Macrobrachium rosenbergii en Guyane française. Elle permet d'aboutir à des recommandations précises et argumentées en matière de recherche comme de développement pour tout décideur impliqué.</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>AgroParisTech, ABIES</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>2010-12-07</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Thesis</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00032/14349/11633.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:language>fr</dc:language>
  <dc:language>en</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00032/14349/</dc:relation>
  <dc:rights>2010 The author, AgroParisTech, ABIES</dc:rights>
</oai_dc:dc>