<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>La pêche du thon a l'appât vivant en Californie</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Doutre, M</dc:creator>
  <dc:description>From February 22nd to April 2nd, 1956, we studied tuna fishing with live bait, as practiced by "tuna-clippers" from the Californian harbour of San Diego. This fishing deals only with two species: the albacore, "yellowfin Tuna" (Neothunnus macropterus) and the skipjack (Katsuwonus pelamis); little tunnies, "black skipjacks" (Euthynnus alleteratus), can also be found, either within an albacore or skipjack shoal, or by themselves. When these fishes are caught, they are either thrown overboard or used as bait (fig, 1). The lower limit weights for these two commercial species are respectively 3.400 kg for albacores and 1.800 kg for skipjacks. Yellowfin tuna can reach weights of up to 180 kg; but these catches are pretty unusual and the average weight is 13 to 18 kg; its market price was set at 320 dollars per US tonne (1.016 kg) in 1953, whereas a tonne of skipjack is worth 280 dollars.</dc:description>
  <dc:description>Du 22 février au Il avril 1956, nous avons assisté à la pêche du thon à l'appât vivant, telle qu'elle est pratiquée par les « tuna-clippers » basés dans le port californien de San Diego. Cette pêche porte uniquement sur deux espèces, l'albacore, « yellowfin Tuna » (Neothunnus macropterus) et le listao, « skipjack » (Katsuwonus pelamis); en cours d'opération, des thonines, « black skipjacks » (Euthynnus alleteratus) peuvent être rencontrées, soit mêlées à un banc d'albacores ou de listaos, soit seules; lorsque ces poissons sont capturés, ils sont rejetés ou conservés pour être utilisés comme aliment pour l'appât (fig, 1). Le poids limite inférieur pour les deux espèces commerciales est respectivement 3,400 kg pour l'albacore et 1,800 kg pour le listao. Le thon aux nageoires jaunes peut atteindre 180 kg; toutefois, les exemples de cette taille sont rares et la moyenne s'établit aux environs de 13 à 18 kg; son prix sur le marché a été fixé en 1953 à 320 dollars la tonne U.S. (1,016 kg), celui du listao étant de 280 dollars la tonne. [OCR NON CONTRÔLE]</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>ISTPM</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>1956-12</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Publication</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/1956/publication-4717.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:source>Revue des Travaux de l'Institut des Pêches Maritimes (0035-2276) (ISTPM), 1956-12 , Vol. 20 , N. 4 , P. 407-443</dc:source>
  <dc:language>fr</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/4717/</dc:relation>
  <dc:rights>Ifremer</dc:rights>
</oai_dc:dc>