<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Hypotaurine and thiotaurine as indicators of sulfide exposure in bivalves and vestimentiferans from hydrothermal vents and cold seeps</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Brand, G</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Horak, R</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Le Bris, Nadine</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Goffredi, S</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Carney, S</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Govenar, B</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Yancey, P</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>Vestimentiferan</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Vesicomyid</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Thiotaurine</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Taurine</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Hypotaurine</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Bathymodiolin</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>Vesicomyid clams, vestimentiferans, and some bathymodiolin mussels from hydrothermal vents and cold seeps possess thiotrophic endosymbionts, high levels of hypotaurine and, in tissues with symbionts, thiotaurine. The latter, a product of hypotaurine and sulfide, may store and/or transport sulfide non-toxically, and the ratio to hypotaurine plus thiotauririe (Th/[H + Th]) may reflect an animal's sulfide exposure. To test this, we analyzed seep and vent animals with in situ sulfide measurements. Calyptogena kilmeri clams occur at high-sulfide seeps in Monterey Canyon, while C. (Vesicomya) pacifica clams occur at seeps with lower levels but take up and metabolize sulfide more effectively. From one seep where they co-occur, both had gill thiotaurine contents at 22-25 mmol kg(-1) wet mass, and while C. (V.) pacifica had a higher blood sulfide level, it had a lower Th/[H + Th] (0.39) than C. kilmeri (0.63). However, these same species from different seeps with lower sulfide exposures had lower ratios. Bathymodiolus thermophilus [East Pacific Rise (EPR 9 degrees 50' N)] from high-(84 mu M) and a low-(7 mu M) sulfide vents had gill ratios of 0.40 and 0.12, respectively. Trophosomes of Riftia pachyptila (EPR 9 degrees 50' N) from medium-(33 mu M) and low-(4 mu M) sulfide vents had ratios of 0.23 and 0.20, respectively (not significantly different). Ridgeia piscesae vestimentiferans (Juan de Fuca Ridge) have very different phenotypes at high- and low-sulfide sites, and their trophosomes had the greatest differences: 0.81 and 0.04 ratios from high- and low-sulfide sites, respectively. Thus Th/ [H + Th] may indicate sulfide exposure levels within species, but not in interspecies comparisons, possibly due to phylogenetic and metabolic differences. Total H + Th was constant within each species (except in R. piscesae); the sum may indicate the maximum potential sulfide load that a species faces.</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>Blackwell science</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>2007-03</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Publication</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/2007/publication-3563.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:identifier>DOI:10.1111/j.1439-0485.2006.00113.x</dc:identifier>
  <dc:source>Marine Ecology (0173-9565) (Blackwell science), 2007-03 , Vol. 28 , N. 1 , P. 208-218</dc:source>
  <dc:language>en</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/3563/</dc:relation>
  <dc:rights>2007 Blackwell Publishing, Inc.</dc:rights>
</oai_dc:dc>