<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Le fond des mers - patrimoine commun de l'humanité</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Piquemal, Alain</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>Histoire Ifremer</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>On August 18th, 1967, H.M. Arvid Pardo, Malta's delegate at the UN, referred to the General Assembly with the question entitled: "Examination of the question of the reservation exclusively for peaceful purposes of the sea-bed and the ocean floor, and the subsoil thereof, underlying the high seas beyond the limits of present national jurisdiction, and the use of their resources in the interests of mankind." (1) This proposal was not the result of pure abstract thinking, but was, on the contrary, the wording of the necessity to adapt marine legislation to the current development state of the international society. However, this evolutive perspective does not exist only economically and technically speaking: it develops in the political field, especially in the development of the nations claim over marine spaces and the genesis of the principle of freedom of high seas. As in any dialectical perspective, legislation interferes with these de facto situations and imposes a number of directions to the study of a legal regime responding to the needs of a changing international society.</dc:description>
  <dc:description>Le 18 août 1967, SE Arvid PARDO, représentant de Malte à l'ONU, saisit l'Assemblée Générale de la question intitulée : "Examen de la question de l'affectation à des fins exclusivement pacifiques du lit des mers ainsi que de leur sous sol, au-delà des limites de la juridiction nationale actuelle et de l'exploitation de leurs ressources dans l'intérêt de l'humanité". (1) Cette proposition n'était pas l'émanation d'une réflexion purement abstraite, mais traduisait au contraire la nécessité d'adapter le droit de la mer à l'état de développement de la société internationale. Cependant, cette perspective évolutive n'existe pas seulement sur le plan économique et technologique : elle se développe au niveau politique, particulièrement dans l'extension des prétentions étatiques sur les espaces maritimes et la genèse du principe de liberté de la haute mer. Comme dans toute perspective dialectique, le droit interfère sur ces situations de fait et impose donc a priori certaines orientations à l'étude d'un régime juridique répondant aux besoins d'une société internationale en pleine mutation. [OCR NON CONTRÔLE]</dc:description>
  <dc:date>1973</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Report</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/1973/rapport-4803.PDF</dc:identifier>
  <dc:language>fr</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/4803/</dc:relation>
</oai_dc:dc>