<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Review and practical use of genome mapping in aquacultured organisms. Position paper by the Working Group on the Application of Genetics in Fisheries and Mariculture (WGAGFM)</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Boudry, Pierre</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Lapegue, Sylvie</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Guyomard, R.</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>Conservation of genetic diversity</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Triploids</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Recommandation</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Aquaculture</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Fish</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Genome mapping</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Genetic</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>The Working Group on the Application of Genetics in Fisheries and Mariculture (WGAGFM) met in La Rochelle, France from 10-12 March, 2003. Seven persons representing six countries were present. Three terms of reference (ToR) were addressed, while one was deferred until the appropriate information was available for review. WGAGFM first considered ToR a) Review and report on the practical use of genome mapping in aquacultured organisms. Genome maps are used extensively in the production of selected strains of agriculture plants and livestock. Studies on the genome of aquatic animais have been summarised in the WG report. Genome mapping projects in aquaculture exist for most major species and linkage maps are now becoming available. WGAGFM produced four recommendations</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>Report of the Working Group on the Application of Genetics in Fisheries and Mariculture, La Rochelle, France, Ref. ICES CM 2003/F:01, 21 p.</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>2003-03-10</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Conference article</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/2003/acte-3301.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:language>en</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/3301/</dc:relation>
</oai_dc:dc>