<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Gestion de l'eau douce et conchyliculture en Charente-Maritime</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Masson, Daniel</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>Hydraulique</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Eau douce</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Sociologie</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Agriculture</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Conchylicultue</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Aquaculture</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>The wetlands of Charente-Maritime represent 100,000 ha and are classified in three categories: flooded marshland valleys, freshwater marshes (farmed land) and coastal salt marshes (traditional and modern shellfish farms). The economic character of the latter two categories gives rise to conflicts of use. Both the agricultural and aquacultural professions are particularly sensitive to these conflicts due to the difficult economic times they are currently experiencing. The main issue is freshwater management, in both its qualitative and quantitative aspects. Charente-Maritime climate is characterised by rainy winters and dry summers and all players need water (or wish to evacuate it) during the same periods. It is thus necessary to mediate disputes or even manage crises that arise.</dc:description>
  <dc:description>Les zones humides de Charente-Maritime représentent 100 000 ha et se répartissent en trois catégories : le marais mouillé (partie inondable des vallées), le marais doux desséché (objet d'une exploitation agricole) et le marais salé (exploité par l'aquaculture traditionnelle ou nouvelle). L'utilisation économique de ces deux derniers compartiments provoque des conflits d'usage d'autant plus susceptibles de dégénérer que les professions conchylicoles et agricoles traversent actuellement de graves difficultés économique. Le principal motif de conflit est bien évidemment la gestion de l'eau douce, tant du point de vue quantitatif que qualitatif. Le climat de Charente-Maritime est caractérisé par des hivers pluvieux et des étés secs: tout le monde a besoin (ou veut se débarrasser) de l'eau aux mêmes moments. Il faut donc arbitrer les litiges, voire gérer les crises qui résultent de cette situation.</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>IFREMER</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>1994</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Publication</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/1994/publication-3231.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:source>Equinoxe (IFREMER), 1994 , Vol. 51 , P. 15-22</dc:source>
  <dc:language>fr</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/3231/</dc:relation>
</oai_dc:dc>