<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>ENSO signals in the vicinity of New Caledonia, South Western Pacific</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Delcroix, T</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Lenormand, O</dc:creator>
  <dc:description>Data collected in an area enclosing New Caledonia are analysed both for the open ocean (17 degrees S-27 degrees S, 169 degrees E-170 degrees E; 1972-1992) and for one point in its lagoon (1967-1993), in order to improve our knowledge of the regional environment, with emphasis on seasonal and interannual (i.e. ENSO) variability. Long-term means and seasonal changes in surface wind, sea-surface temperature and salinity, and 0-400 m temperature, salinity and zonal geostrophic current are first described to Set the context. Through comparisons with the Southern Oscillation Index (SOI), it is demonstrated that there are signals in these parameters that are connected with ENSO. During the warm phase of ENSO (SOI &lt; 0, El Nino), we observed saltier-than-average anomalies in sea-surface salinity (similar to 0.2), 0-50 m cold temperature anomalies (similar to 0.5 degrees C) contrasting with the well-known warm eastern equatorial Pacific anomalies, together with westerly (similar to 10 m(2) s(-2)) and southerly (similar to 4 m(2) s-2) wind anomalies over a large part of the studied area. Conversely, anomalies of similar magnitude but of opposite sign were detected during the cold phase of ENSO (SOI &gt; 0; La Nina). The mechanisms which connect these regional anomalies to ENSO evolution at low-latitudes are qualitatively discussed.</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>Gauthier-Villars</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>1997</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Publication</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00093/20410/18077.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:source>Oceanolica Acta (0399-1784) (Gauthier-Villars), 1997 , Vol. 20 , N. 3 , P. 481-491</dc:source>
  <dc:language>en</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00093/20410/</dc:relation>
</oai_dc:dc>