<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Effect of different food levels on the growth and survival of laboratory-reared sea-bass larvae (Dicentrarchus Labrax (L.))</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Barahona-fernandes, Maria Helena</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Girin, Michel</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>Histoire Ifremer</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>Four batches of 7 500 larvae were during a period of one month in 150 l tanks at 18° C. The first one was fed on the basis of estimates of the required daily amount of organisms that were made by one of the authors ; the second batch was fed on the average of the estimates made by both aushare ; the third and the. fourth batches were fed, respectively, with, 20% above and 20% below this average.  The densities of food in the tanks varied from 0 to 16 organisms/ml before the daily meal and from 1 to 25 organisms/ml after it. There Was no significant difference in the final weight or length of the larvae, although the larvae receiving the highest food level showed a significantly better growth at the age of 15 days. Survival seemed to be better at lower feeding levels. The food conversion rates varied from 34.1 to 15.3 (wet weight) and from 18.7 to 8.4 (dry weight). The best: rates were obtained at the lowest feeding level.</dc:description>
  <dc:description>Quatre lots de 7 500 larves de bar sont élevés pendant un mois dans des bacs de 150 l d 18° C. Ces larvee reçoivent quotidiennement des quantités différentes de proies vivantes. Le premier lot est nourri sUr la base d'une estimation de la quantité de nourriture à donner faite par une seule personne, le second sUr la base de la moyenne des estimations faites par deux personnes, le troisième et le quatrième respectivement 20 % au-dessus et au-dessous de cette moyenne.  La concentration des proies dans les bacs varie de 0 à 16 proies/ml avant la distribution des repas et de 1 à 25 proies/ml après, Malgré une croissance plus rapide des larves suralimentées, pendant les deux premières semaines, aucune différence significative ne subsiste enfin d'expérience. La survie finale semble meilleure dans les lots recevant moins de nourriture. Les taux de conversion de la nourriture varient de 34,1 à 15,5 en poids humide et de 18,7 à 8,4 en poids sec. Le meilleur résultat est obtenu pour le lot le moins alimenté.</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>Publ. CNEXO (France) (Actes Colloq.)(no. 7)</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>1977-05</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Conference article</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/1977/publication-6066.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:language>en</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/6066/</dc:relation>
</oai_dc:dc>