<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Un modèle général de d'évolution de l'océan indien</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Sahabi, Mohamed</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>Indian ocean</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Model</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Map</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Fracture zone</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Intraplate deformation</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Kinematics</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Ocean Indien</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Modellisation</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Carte</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Zone fracture</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Faille transformante</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Cinématique</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>The last global synthesis of the evolution of the Indian ocean which satisfactorily describes the kinematics of the five major plates, up to the initial stages, dates back to Norton and Sclater [1979]. Although the most recent phases of evolution have been largely detailed, in particular in the proximity of the triple junction, the initial stages of evolution have been generally described by models quite speculative and generally only constrained by pairs of plates.

The recentmost gravity data based on the altimetric satellites SEASAT, GEOSAT and ERS1 [Sandwell and Smith, 1992] give an homogenoeus image of sea-floor topography. These data, declassified to the south of 30°S, reveal previously unknowkn features of the sea-floor fabric and allow to further detail the geometry of fracture zones. This thesis presents a general model of evolution which takes account of these major physiographic features (fracture zones) as well as all the constraints provided by detailed works and concerning key areas such as the Kerguelen- Broken Ridge system and Mozambique continental shelf. The kinematic reconstructions, here proposed, are substantially based on the assumption that fracture zones are traces of relative motion between plates. Consequently segments of fracture zones used to define a kinematic stage are consistent with sets of small circles. Definition of kinematic stages and choice of the stage rotation poles have been performed by pursuing the objective of internal coherence of the model among the five plates. The approximations generated by such a global "stage by stage" model cannot resolve neither transitions from one stage to another nor the 2nd order kinematic rearrangements, which can be also masked by intraplate deformations.

The whole work has been carried out by following four main steps : 1) collection and synthesis of marine and satellite geophysical data (bathymetry, gravity, altimetry, magnetics); 2) digitization of data; 3) computer generated paleogeographic maps based on kinematic reconstruction and 4) interpretation of the resulting maps and proposal of an evolutionary model which takes account of all the geological constraints.

Because all the basins created between Africa and Antarctica are located south of 30°S, the reconstructions for each stage were precisely referred to Africa and Antartica plates whereas India and Australia were then included in the puzzle. Basins located NW of Australia present enough evidence to support the hypothesis of a "Greater India Plate" containing Block North India and the India s.s. plate. The adoption of this last hypoyhesis represents a strong constraint to be included into the general evolutionary model.

It is possible to obtain, without intraplate deformation a remarkable morphological assemblage of different margins, which provide a beginning of kinematics reconstructions. The Socotra Bank (Arabian sea) and the Mozambique Ridge occupied slightly different position; as a consequence, they moved with respect to the adjacient fixed margins. Similarly micro continental blocks such as Aghulas Plateau, Sri-Lanka and Tasmania had exhibited, for a given timespan, a different evolution with respect to their major plates. Furthermore, a reconstruction gap in the south of Madagascar suggests that the northern part of Madagascar Ridge is of continental origin.

The analysis of transform directions suggest the absence of significant changes in relative motion between magnetic anomaly 20 and the Present except for Africa and India. Between Africa and Antartica recent, satellite-derived data reveal major change in plates trajectories between anomalies 32 and 20-24. Another major change occurred little before anomaly 34 at around 90-93 My.

The elongated topography of aseismic ridges in the Indian ocean, frequently related to hot spot traces can be associated with triple junction at a moment when one of the branch aded as 2nd order limit. Ninetyeast Ridge and Chagos-Laccadive Ridges coincide to original transform directions on turn associated to triple junction. In summary, the main results of this work can be concluded as following:

- At the scale of the whole Indian ocean the kinematic evolution of plates can be described by major phases (each during 20-30 My) which are also recognizable in other oceans. In this context the occurrence of 2nd order rearrangements of regional extent did not significantly affect the global evolution.

- The genesis of abnormal structures i.e. aseismic ridges, generally associated with the activity of hot spots, is strictly related to kinematic rearrangements. These structures can be viewed as the consequences and not the causes of kinematic reorganisations.

- A major plate reorganisation occurring during middle Cretaceous (90-93 My) and documented all over the other oceans of the Earth is also confirmed in the Indian ocean.

- The continental margin located to the west of the Australia correspond to a portion of one plate locked to the India plate and currently mostly disappeared beneath the Asiatic continent. The structures observables on this australian margin have recorded the motion of that ancestral plate, so supporting the hypothesis of a "Greater India" plate.</dc:description>
  <dc:description>Depuis le travail de Norton et Sclater en 1979, l'évolution de l'océan Indien n'a plus fait l'objet d'une synthèse globale capable de lier, en remontant jusqu'aux phases initiales, les mouvements relatifs entre les cinq plaques majeures qui le composent Les phases récentes ont été étudiées avec beaucoup de précision, surtout au voisinage du point triple, mais les phases initiales n'ont donné lieu qu'à des modèles plus ou moins spéculatifs, en général limités à la cinématique d'un couple de plaques.

Contrastant avec les données océanographiques, très irrégulièrement réparties, la carte de l'anomalie de gravité du monde de Sandwell et Smith, tirée des données altimétriques SEASAT, GEOSAT et ERS1, ouvertes au public récemment au sud de 30°S, dorme une image homogène des fonds. Les traits majeurs de l'évolution, et en particulier les failles transformantes, y sont très clairement marqués.

Ce travail présente une synthèse générale prenant en compte ces traits majeurs ainsi que les nombreuses contraintes fournies par les travaux réalisés ces dernières années sur, et autour, de structures clés comme le système Kerguelenride de Broken ou le plateau continental du Mozambique. D s'appuie essentiellement sur le principe selon lequel les failles transformantes sont les marques des mouvements relatifs des couples de plaques; la condition est que l'on puisse montrer que les segments de faille retenus pour reconstituer une étape s'ordonnent bien suivant une famille de petits cercles. C'est la cohérence de l'ensemble du système, ici constitué de cinq plaques, qui justifie en dernier ressort le choix des pôles de rotation et celui de la longueur des étapes. Il s'agit en tout état de cause d'une légère approximation qui ne détaille ni les passages d'une phase à une autre, ni les changements de second ordre dont on a estimé qu'ils pouvaient se confondre avec la déformation intra-plaque.

Le travail d'analyse et de démonstration s'appuie essentiellement sur des cartes (volume 2). Toutes les données principales (bathymétrie, altimétrie, gravimétrie, magnétisme, données structurales) ont été compilées et numérisées; mais la densité des informations est très inégale : au sud de 30° S, l'image morphologique du fond est fournie avec un grand détail par la couverture altimétrique qui bénéficie d'une très grande densité de mesures. Pour chaque époque, le raisonnement se base sur la reconstitution entre Afrique et Antarctique; l'Inde et l'Australie pouvant ensuite être intégrées. Les bassins situés au NW de l'Australie offrent des données suffisamment nettes pour que l'on puisse confirmer l'hypothèse d'une "Grande Inde" solidaire de l'Inde proprement dite. L'adoption de cette hypothèse ajoute une contrainte très forte au modèle d'évolution générale, dans la mesure où on parvient à le rendre cohérent. Il est possible d'obtenir, sans déformation intra-plaque, un assemblage morphologique remarquable des différentes marges qui doit servir de point de départ à un modèle d'évolution. Le banc de Socotra (mer d'Arabie) et la ride de Mozambique occupaient à l'origine des positions un peu différentes de celles qu'elles occupent actuellement par rapport aux marges adjacentes. Des micro-blocs continentaux comme le plateau des Aiguilles, Sri-Lanka et la Tasmanie ont eu également, à une certaine époque, une évolution distincte de celle des plaques majeures. Un hiatus particulier correspondant à la partie septentrionale du plateau de Madagascar suggère une origine continentale. L'analyse des directions transformantes suggère l'absence de changements de direction notable entre l'anomalie magnétique 20 et l'Actuel, sauf entre l'Inde et l'Afrique. Entre l'Afrique et l'Antarctique, les données altimétriques révèlent clairement la virgation majeure de la trajectoire entre les anomalies magnétiques 20-24 et 32. Un autre changement majeur se situe un peu avant l'anomalie magnétique 34, vers 90-93 Ma.

La topographie allongée des structures asismiques de l'océan Indien, assimilées souvent à des traces de points chauds, ont pris naissance systématiquement sur des points triples, à des époques où l'une des branches fonctionnait en "frontière de second ordre". Ninetyeast et Chagos-Laccadives coïncident pour leur part de très près avec des directions transformantes également associées à des points triples.

En définitif, les principaux résultats qui ressortent de ce travail sont :

- A l'échelle de l'océan Indien, l'évolution des plaques peut être décrite par de grandes phases (20 à 30 Ma), que l'on retrouve généralement dans les autres océans du globe. Cette hypothèse n'exclut, pas par ailleurs, l'existence de changements de second ordre de portée plus régionale.

- La formation des structures anormales interprétées comme résultant de l'activité de points chauds coïncide étroitement avec des réajustements cinématiques. Ces structures anormales sont la conséquence et non la cause des réorganisations cinématiques.

- La confirmation de la réorganisation majeure du Crétacé moyen (90-93 Ma) survenue à l'échelle de tous les océans du globe.

- Les marges de l'ouest de l'Australie correspondent à une portion de plaque située à l'origine au nord de llnde, dont l'autre partie a disparu sous l'Asie. Les structures laissées sur la plaque australienne permettent de contraindre la cinématique de cette plaque. Le modèle proposé montre que l'on peut intégrer ces contraintes à celles de la plaque Inde, confirmant ainsi la notion de "Grande Inde".</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>Université de Bretagne Occidentale</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>1993-12-02</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Thesis</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/1993/these-614.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:language>fr</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/614/</dc:relation>
</oai_dc:dc>