<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>A laboratory model system for analysing microbial interactions occurring in anoxic estuarine sediments.</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Herbert, R</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Keith, S</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>Chromatium vinosum</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Desulfovibrio desulfuricans</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Clostridium butyricum</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Biogeochemistry</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Models</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Bacteria</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Detritus</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Mineralization</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Anoxic sediments</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Estuarine sedimentation</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Analytical techniques</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Carbon cycle</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Interspecific relationships</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Microbiology</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>Defined mixed populations of Clostridium butyricum, Desulfovibrio desulfuricans and Chromatium vinosum co-existed for long periods when grown in a single stage chemostat with glucose as sole carbon source. The nature and availability of the inorganic nitrogen source exerted a major effect on carbon flow in the experimental system. The data show that both the C. butyricum and D. desulfuricans isolates can utilise NO sub(3) as an e super(-)acceptor with an increase in cell yield. Under these growth conditions the free S super(2-) levels were lower resulting in more stable mixed populations. In addition the data show that the C. butyricum produces more oxidised fermentation end-products (acetate) when NO sub(3) super(-) was available and more reduced products (butyrate) when grown on NH sub(4) super(+).</dc:description>
  <dc:description>Des populations mixtes de Clostridium butyricum, Desulfovibrio desulfuricans, et Chromatium vinosum co-existent pendant de longues périodes, lorsqu'elles se développent dans un chemostat à une seule étape avec du glucose pour seule source de carbone. La nature et la disponibilité de la source d'azote inorganique exercent un effet important sur le flux de carbone du système expérimental. Les données montrent que les isolats de Clostridium bulyricum.czux de Desulfovibrio desulfuricans et ceux de Chromatium vinosum peuvent utiliser NO3 comme accepteur d'électrons, avec une augmentation de la production des cellules. Sous ces conditions de croissance les niveaux des ions S2" libres sont plus faibles et il en résulte des populations mixtes
plus stables. Les expériences montrent également que Clostridium butyricum fabrique plus de produits finaux de fermentation oxydés (acetate) lorsque NO3" est disponible, et plus de produits réduits (butyrate) lorsqu'elle
se développe sur NH4 .</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>Actes de colloques. Ifremer Brest [ACTES COLLOQ. IFREMER.]. 1986</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>1984-10</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Conference article</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/1984/acte-947.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:language>en</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/947/</dc:relation>
</oai_dc:dc>