<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Analysis of random nonlinear water waves: the Stokes-Woodward technique</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Elfouhaily, Tanos</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Joelson, Maminirina</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Guignard, Stéphan</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Branger, Hubert</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Thompson, Donald</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Chapron, Bertrand</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Vandemark, Douglas</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>Frequency modulation</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Amplitude modulation</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Bispectrum</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Vertical asymmetry</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Horizontal asymmetry</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Wave wave interaction</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Mode coupling</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Fluid mechanics</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Modulation de fréquence</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Modulation d'amplitude</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Bispectre</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Dissymétrie horisontale</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Dissymétrie verticale</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Interaction vague vague</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Couplage de mode</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Mécaniques des fluides</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>A generalization of the Woodward's theorem is applied to the case of random signals jointly modulated in amplitude and frequency. This yields the signal spectrum and a rather robust estimate of the bispectrum. Furthermore, higher order statistics that quantify the amount of energy in the signal due to nonlinearities, e.g., wave-wave interaction in the case of water waves, can be inferred. Considering laboratory wind generated water waves, comparisons between the presented generalization and more standard techniques allow to extract the spectral energy due to nonlinear wave-wave interactions. It is shown that our analysis extends the domain of standard spectral estimation techniques from narrow-band to broad-band processes.</dc:description>
  <dc:description>Une généralisation du théorème de Woodward est appliquée au cas d'un signal aléatoire modulé en amplitude et en fréquence. Le spectre du signal ainsi qu'une estimation robuste du bispectre sont obtenues grace à cette nouvelle technique. En sus, des moments statistiques d'ordre supérieur quantifiant l'énergie due aux non linéarités, i.e., aux interactions entre vagues dans le cas des ondes de surface, sont évalués. L'énergie spectrale d'interaction non linéaire est extraite grâce à la comparaison de la présente méthode, à des méthodes plus classiques lors de l'analyse de signaux de vagues de vent fort générées en soufflerie. Il est finalement montré que notre technique étend le domaine des méthodes d'estimation spectrale aux processus large bande.</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>Elsevier</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>2003-03</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Publication</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/2003/publication-741.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:identifier>DOI:10.1016/S1631-0721(03)00055-X</dc:identifier>
  <dc:source>Comptes Rendus Mecanique (1631-0721) (Elsevier), 2003-03 , Vol. 331 , N. 3 , P. 189-196</dc:source>
  <dc:language>en</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/741/</dc:relation>
  <dc:rights>2003 Académie des sciences/Éditions scientifiques et médicales Elsevier SAS. All rights reserved</dc:rights>
</oai_dc:dc>