<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Integration of discards in the roundnose grenadier stock assessment in ICES division Vb, subaera VI, VII</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Pawlowski, Lionel</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Lorance, Pascal</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>abundance</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>deep fishing</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>discards</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>stock assessment</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>roundnose grenadier</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>abondance</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>pêche profonde</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>rejets</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>évaluation de la ressource</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>grenadier de roche</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>We present a series of exploratory stock assessments for roundnose grenadier (Coryphaenoides rupestris) from estimates of catch data based on information and assumption of discards and landing statistics. It is a common practice to consider landings data as a substitute of catch data to perform stock assessments. When a significant portion of the catch is discarded, this assumption is likely to be misleading as assessment methods will provide underestimated stock size.</dc:description>
  <dc:description>Une série d'évaluations de stock exploratoires pour le grenadier de roche (Coryphaenoides rupestris) a été réalisée à partir d'estimations de capture basées sur  l'évaluation des rejets et sur les statistiques des débarquements. Pour les évaluations de stock, il est courant de considérer que les données des débarquements correspondent aux données des captures. Mais lorsqu'une portion significative de la capture est rejetée, il est alors fort probable que les méthodes de travail donneront des résultats faussés et que la taille du stock sera sous-estimée.</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>Approche systémique des pêches Boulogne 5,6 et 7 novembre 2008</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>2008-09-30</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Poster</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/2008/rapport-7440.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:language>en</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/7440/</dc:relation>
</oai_dc:dc>