<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>Reproductive dynamics of swordfish (Xiphias gladius) in the southwestern Indian Ocean (Reunion Island). Part 2: fecundity and spawning pattern</dc:title>
  <dc:creator>Poisson, Francois</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Fauvel, Christian</dc:creator>
  <dc:subject>Xiphias gladius</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Swordfish</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Reproductive strategy</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Gravimetric method</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Image processing</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Spawning frequency</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Indian Ocean</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Fecundity</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>Reproduction</dc:subject>
  <dc:description>Batch fecundity and relative fecundity of swordfish (Xiphias gladius) in the southwestern Indian Ocean were estimated from seven gravid swordfish females (size range 127-225 cm lower jaw-to-fork length, LJFL) with unovulated, hydrated oocytes collected onboard Reunion-based (France) longline swordfish fishing vessels between December 1999 to January 2001. To investigate the spawning pattern of swordfish, we used data collected through a combination of two at sea sampling regimes. A total of 17 007 geo-located size data of swordfish were recorded during 8 years (1993-2001) and a total of 1727 (size range 75-289 cm, LJFL) swordfish gonads (1107 females and 620 males) were sampled from May 1998 to January 2001. The estimated batch fecundity ranged from 995 000 hydrated oocytes for the smallest ripe female to 4.3 millions for the largest female sampled measuring respectively 127 to 225 cm in curved length (LJFL). The relative fecundity ranged from 25 to 72 hydrated oocytes per gram of body weight. We found that batch fecundity was positively correlated with fish length and that the older/larger females have earlier and longer spawning seasons than younger/smaller females. These findings suggested that older/larger females which are seasonally migrating in this spawning ground seem to play a major role in reproductive success of the species in producing significantly more offspring than younger females during an extended spawning season. Examination of the length-frequency date from the fishery indicated that the young fish are resident around Reunion and around the seamounts off Reunion Island. Our results highlight the important role of the older/larger females in the reproductive capacity of southwestern Indian Ocean stock. We discuss the potential implications of fishing the older/larger females for this stock in terms of reproduction and recruitment.</dc:description>
  <dc:description>La fécondité par acte de ponte et la fécondité relative chez l'espadon (Xiphias gladius) dans le sud-ouest de l'océan Indien sont estimées d'après sept femelles de taille comprise entre 127 et 225 cm (de l'extrémité de la mâchoire inférieure à la fourche caudale) ; celles-ci ayant atteint la maturité sexuelle, les ovaires contenant des ovocytes hydratés. Ces femelles ont été pêchées entre décembre 1999 et janvier 2001, par des palangriers ciblant l'espadon et basés à La Réunion. La stratégie de la reproduction chez l'espadon a été étudiée en utilisant des données collectées au cours de deux campagnes d'échantillonnages en mer : soit 17&amp;#8201;007 mensurations géo-référencées d'espadons, de 75 à 289 cm, qui ont été enregistrées durant les 8 années d'étude (1993-2001) et 1727 gonades d'espadon (1107 femelles et 620 mâles) prélevées entre mai 1998 et juin 2001.La fécondité par acte de ponte estimée varie de 995 000 ovocytes hydratés, pour la plus petite femelle (127 cm), à 4,3 millions pour la plus grande femelle (225 cm). La fécondité par acte de ponte est corrélée positivement à la taille du poisson. La fécondité relative s'étend de 25 à 72 ovocytes hydratés par gramme de poids de corps. Les femelles les plus âgées/grandes pondent plus tôt et sur une période plus grande que les plus jeunes/petites femelles. Ainsi, les femelles plus âgées/grandes qui migrent de façon saisonnière vers cette aire de ponte, contribueraient plus largement au renouvellement de l'espèce en produisant de façon significative davantage de recrues que les femelles plus jeunes et ceci pendant une saison de ponte plus étendue. Par ailleurs, les jeunes individus semblent séjourner aux abords de l'île de La Réunion et des monts sous-marins situés au large. Nos résultats soulignent l'importance du rôle des femelles âgées/grandes dans la capacité reproductrice du stock d'espadon du sud-ouest de l'océan Indien. Les implications potentielles de la pêche : des femelles âgées et de grandes tailles sont discutées pour ce stock, du point de vue de la reproduction et du recrutement.</dc:description>
  <dc:publisher>EDP Sciences</dc:publisher>
  <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
  <dc:type>text</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Publication</dc:type>
  <dc:format>application/pdf</dc:format>
  <dc:identifier>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/2009/publication-6354.pdf</dc:identifier>
  <dc:identifier>DOI:10.1051/alr/2009012</dc:identifier>
  <dc:source>Aquatic Living Resources (0990-7440) (EDP Sciences), 2009 , Vol. 22 , N. 1 , P. 59-68</dc:source>
  <dc:language>en</dc:language>
  <dc:relation>http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00000/6354/</dc:relation>
  <dc:rights>2009 EDP Sciences</dc:rights>
</oai_dc:dc>